<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mary's choice declared in a sermon preached at the funeral of the Right Honourable Lady Mary Wharton, late wife of the Honourable Sir Thomas Wharton, Knight of the Bath, at Edlington in the county of York together with a narrative of the religious and holy life, and death of that excellent lady / by P.W., Rector of Edlington.</title>
            <author>P. W. (Peter Watkinson), d. 1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 167 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65259</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1079</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38495</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17513006</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17513006</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106528</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65259)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106528)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1107:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mary's choice declared in a sermon preached at the funeral of the Right Honourable Lady Mary Wharton, late wife of the Honourable Sir Thomas Wharton, Knight of the Bath, at Edlington in the county of York together with a narrative of the religious and holy life, and death of that excellent lady / by P.W., Rector of Edlington.</title>
                  <author>P. W. (Peter Watkinson), d. 1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert White, for Henry Mortlock ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wharton, Mary Carey, --  Lady, 1615-1674.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Luke X, 17 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106528:1"/>
            <p>Mary's Choice Declared in a SERMON Preached at the FUNERAL Of the Right Honourable Lady MARY WHARTON, Late Wife of the Honourable Sir <hi>Thomas Wharton,</hi> Knight of the <hi>Bath;</hi> At <hi>Edlington</hi> in the County of <hi>York.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with a Narrative of the Religious and Holy Life, and Death of that excellent Lady.</p>
            <p>By <hi>P. W.</hi> Rector of <hi>Edlington.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Favour is deceitful, and Beauty is vain; but a Woman that feareth the Lord, ſhe ſhall be praiſed,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 30.31.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Vivit poſt funera virtus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Robert White,</hi> for <hi>Henry Mortlock,</hi> and are to be ſold at the White Hart in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Hall, and at the Phoenix in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:106528:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106528:2"/>
            <p>Viro verè Honorabili, &amp; omnigenà Virtute ac Pietate inſigni,</p>
            <p>Domino <hi>Thomae Wharton</hi> Equiti Ord. Balnei Patrono ſuo Colendiſſimo:</p>
            <p>Nec non D. <hi>Philippo Wharton</hi> Armigero unico ejus, &amp; optimae Spei Filio:</p>
            <p>Unà cum <hi>Elizabetha</hi> ipſius uxore, ac viri Generoſiſſimi D. <hi>Richardi Hutton</hi> de Goldsborough Armigeri Filia unica:</p>
            <p>Praecorditer adhuc lugentibus Conjugem dilectiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam, Matrem deſideratiſſimam:</p>
            <p>Hanc qualemcun<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Conciunculam Funebrem</p>
            <p>Et annexam Narratiunculam In perpetuae obſervantiae Teſtimonium. Funebrem</p>
            <p>D. D. D. Iiſdem omni Obſequio Devinctiſſimus, <hi>P. W.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:106528:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106528:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Curteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Have here given thee a rude draught of a very exact Preſident; preſenting thee with an excellent Subject, but very inartificially handled. My acquaintance with this excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Lady was very ſhort, ſhe not living two years, after I had the happineſs to know her; yet had that ſhort time been more carefully improved, thou hadſt been enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained with much more than is here repreſented. But this is the common miſtake of us miſerable mortals: we ſet not that price, we ought, upon preſent Vertue, nor are we ſo provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, as to enjoy the benefit of it ſo fully as we might, whilſt we have it: only when it is taken from us, it leaves behind it a deep ſenſe of our loſs, and want of what we had, together with an helpleſs repentance, that we made no better uſe of it, whilſt we had it. Beſides this diſadvantage: I who am the moſt unworthy of all her former acquaintances in the Miniſtry, and moſt unable and unfit for ſuch an undertaking, yet am neceſſarily put upon this task (none other being at hand, with whom ſhe hath in this ſhort while ſo frequently converſed) by reaſon of my Relation to her, and near neighbourhood. This Picture deſerved an <hi>Apelles,</hi> to have drawn it to the Life: and great pity it is, that ſo choice a piece ſhould be expoſed to thy view with ſuch dull and dusky colours, and by ſuch an unskillful hand. But I queſtion not, but that every pious and ingenuous Reader will from theſe hints, repreſent to himſelf much more
<pb facs="tcp:106528:4"/>than I have or can expreſs; and by his larger apprehenſion ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply my defects. Thou haſt the Sermon in the ſame Method, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it was Preached, without addition of any chief head: only in the tranſcribing diverſe paſſages are conſiderably enlarged; part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from what was then prepared, but could not be delivered in the ſhort time allotted for ſuch diſcourſes (there being alſo many Noble and Honourable Perſons to ſolemnize her Funeral, who had many miles to their home) and partly from what did occur in the tranſcribing, which I judged ſutable to the Diſcourſe in hand. The Narrative is, in good part, ſuch as was ſpoken at the Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral; but here very much enlarged; not only upon the former ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, but moſtly upon further information of many particulars, whereof I had no knowledge, before this was intended to be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed. I aſſure thee (Reader) it is not from any ambition the Authour hath to appear in Print, that hath made this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe publick. The conſcience of his own inſufficiency for ſuch undertakings hath hitherto kept him within the bounds of privacy: which if he now ſeem to have tranſgreſſed, thy charity will ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impute it to ſome other urgent cauſe, than his own choice. It is but loſt labour, and <hi>actum agere,</hi> to cenſure his weakneſs, who himſelf hath done it before thee. The beſt uſe thou canſt make of what he hath done, is ſeriouſly to apply, what thou findeſt to concern thy ſelf, and to imitate the example here laid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee; chooſing with her <hi>that good Part,</hi> whereof our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour hath given aſſurance, that it ſhall not be taken away from thee. That both thou and I may make ſuch uſe of what is here preſented, ſhall be the Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>The moſt unworthy in Goſpel-Work,</hi> P. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106528:4"/>
            <head>Mary's Choice.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>St. LUKE X. XLII.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>But one thing is needful; and Mary hath choſen that good Part, which ſhall not be taken away from her.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Text is a part of our Saviour's Anſwer to <hi>Martha</hi>'s expoſtulation with him for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining her Siſter from her aſſiſtance, whilſt all the Work lay upon her hands, in making proviſion for him and his Diſciples; <hi>Lord</hi> (ſaith ſhe) <hi>doſt thou not take care,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 40.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mary</hi> being ſo well employed, ſitting at his feet, and hearing his Word, (<hi>ver.</hi> 39.) well might our Saviour have ſharply rebuked <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha</hi>'s obſtreperous and unſeaſonable diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; but with all mildneſs he only admoniſheth her, how much <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>'s employment was to be preferred before hers; <hi>Martha, Martha,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Repetitio no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis eſt indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium dilectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, aut for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>è movendae intentionis, ut audiret attentiús. <hi>Aug. de verb. Dom. Serm.</hi> 26. <hi>Aret.</hi> and others <hi>in loc.</hi>
               </note> (ſaith he) <hi>thou art careful and troubled,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 41.</p>
            <p>Diverſe Interpreters ſuppoſe here a vehement reprehenſion of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha</hi>'s over-much ſolicitude for things not neceſſary; and her neglect of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106528:5"/>the <hi>one thing</hi> neceſſary, which <hi>Mary</hi> had choſen. But others ſuppoſe, that the words do not ſo much import a reprehenſion of <hi>Martha</hi>'s loving care, as a defence of <hi>Mary</hi> who was better employ'd, and therefore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable,<note place="margin">Non opus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendit, ſed munus diſtinxit, <hi>Aug. ubi ſupra Serm.</hi> 27. So alſo <hi>Ambr. in loc. Simo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> de Caſſ.</hi> l. 9. c. 33. <hi>Bucer</hi> and others, <hi>in loc.</hi>
               </note> though ſhe did neglect inferiour buſineſs.</p>
            <p>In this part of his Anſwer, which is to be the Subject of our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; we may obſerve,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. An Admonition to <hi>Martha;</hi> That <hi>one thing is needful.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. A commendation of <hi>Mary,</hi> for her choice of that <hi>one thing;</hi> Mary <hi>hath choſen,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
            <p>In treating of the former of theſe, we ſhall enquire by way of Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, 1. What this <hi>one thing is?</hi> 2. How it is called <hi>one?</hi> 3. In what reſpects it is ſaid to be neceſſary.</p>
            <p n="1">I. For the firſt, it is evident in the Text it ſelf, that this <hi>one thing</hi> is that <hi>good part,</hi> which <hi>Mary</hi> had choſen: and not that abſtracted <hi>Monas,</hi> or unity (which ſome ſpeak of (but <hi>extra rem,</hi> beſides the Text, as one ſaith) oppoſed to multiplicity,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Calv.</hi> in loc.</note> nor yet that unity which is oppoſed to Schiſme (as St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſeems to take it) nor yet that little which may ſuffice for hoſpitable entertainment,<note place="margin">Aug. de verb. Dom. Serm. <hi>26.</hi> Vid. Theophil. Lyſer. Stella, <hi>&amp;c. in loc.</hi>
               </note> excluding ſuperfluity (as ſome others expound it:) Nor can it be that conceited perfection which the <hi>Popiſh Monks</hi> contend for; ſequeſtring themſelves from all worldly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, that they may attend nothing elſe, but (as they pretend) Divine Contemplation.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hieron. in Thr.</hi> lib. 2. cap. 3. <hi>Bern. Serm.</hi> 5. de aſſumpt. <hi>Mariae. Theoph.</hi> ubi ſupra.</note> Though St. <hi>Jerome,</hi> and other of the Fathers, have by way of alluſion made ſuch uſe of this Text: which yet is far from the purpoſe of our Saviours Words. For can any man think, that this was <hi>Mary</hi>'s conſtant and continual Work, becauſe ſhe was at this time ſo careful to improve this preſent opportunity of her Saviours com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany? We know that God hath ordained, that all men ſhould ſerve him in their ſeveral vocations;<note place="margin">Gal. 5.13.</note> and ſerve one another in Love, in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent performance of each duty in that ſtate of Life, in which Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence hath placed them;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.17.</note> as the Lord hath called every man, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Our Saviour would have us make a wiſe diſtribution of our times: yet ever preferring the beſt employment, when it ſutes with our poſſible leiſure, and ſeaſonable opportunity.</p>
            <p>This <hi>one thing</hi> then here meant, is that which <hi>Mary</hi> makes her preſent buſineſs. To underſtand which, we muſt conſider it with a double re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, 1. To the End. 2. To the Means.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The End, or main thing intended is everlaſting happineſs; which conſiſts in the fruition of God, in neareſt communion with him accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our preſent condition and capacity: which is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Here in Part,<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.8. 1 Pet. 2.3. Eph. 1.14.</note> in ſome foretaſts of Divine Comforts, which it pleaſeth the Lord to allow his Servants, as an earneſt or pledge of that which is prepared for them in Heaven. This conſiſts in the ſenſe and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106528:5"/>feeling of the Love of God, ſhed abroad into our hearts,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.5.</note> by the Holy Ghoſt, and is obtained eſpecially by the exerciſe of Faith and Love.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hereafter we ſhall enjoy him in Eternal Glory,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.4. Phil. 1.23. 1 Cor. 13.12. Pſalm 10.11. Acts 20.22. Luke 22.29. 1 Pet. 1.4. 2 Tim. 4.8. Jam 1.12. Phil. 3.14. Joh. 10 28. Mat. 25.34. E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h 1.14. Col. 1.5. Heb. 5 9. 1 Cor. 2 9. Pſalm 31.19. Iſa 64 4. Phil. 3.13, 14. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Eccleſ. 12.13.</note> of which we are uncapable, whilſt we remain cloathed with this mortal and corruptible Tabernacle: which therefore the Saints ſo earneſtly deſire to put off, that they may be with Chriſt: For then in perfect Glory we ſhall ſee him face to face, in the fulneſs of joy, and pleaſures for evermore. This is that Inheritance, Kingdom, Crown, Price, Life, Joy, Glory, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo oft mentioned in the Scripture: and which is ſaid to be purchaſed, prepared, and laid up for all thoſe that obey him, love, and fear him; that put their truſt in him, and diligently ſeek him. This is that <hi>one thing,</hi> which we are required to ſeek, to lay hold on, to take by force, to fight, ſtrive, and run for, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. This <hi>one thing</hi> is likewiſe conſidered with reference to the Means whereby the mentioned End is obtained. To attend which was St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s greateſt care and buſineſs: which is indeed work enough for a man to do in his whole Life, with all his might. This is the whole of man, <hi>i. e.</hi> all he can do to attain happineſs. It is the <hi>one thing,</hi> which comprehends <hi>All,</hi> that is to be done in order to Eternal Life; therefore muſt needs be very extenſive. But we ſhall confine our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, eſpecially to that part of this <hi>All,</hi> which is in the Context, <hi>verſ.</hi> 39. <hi>viz.</hi> Hearing the Word.</p>
            <p>One obſerves,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gualt.</hi> in Luc. 10.39. Acts 22 3.</note> that Diſciples were wont to ſit at the feet of their Teachers, as a ſign of Humility and obſervance. So St. <hi>Paul</hi> was ſaid, to be brought up at the feet of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> being perfectly by him inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Law. In this (ſaith that Authour) conſiſts the true worſhip of God, and the Salvation of man.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That we caſt our ſelves at the feet of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Quanto hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militi, ſede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, tanto am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plius capiebat. <hi>Aug. de verb. Dom. Serm.</hi> 27.</note> 
               <hi>i. e.</hi> that we hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our ſelves before him with a contrite heart, and tremble at his Word, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.2.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That we receive his Word by a true and lively Faith; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets in us true Love to God, and exhilarates the ſoul, by the ſweet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of the promiſes contained in the Word: whence proceeds, an earneſt and ardent ſtudy, and deſire to obey the commands of God. Which is the cauſe, that the fruit of the Word ſo heard, diffuſeth it ſelf through the whole Life. Thus we ſee what this <hi>one thing</hi> is.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Now we are to conſider, how it is faid to be <hi>one?</hi> It is <hi>one,</hi> not excluſively (as though whilſt we attend this, we were bound to neglect all other duties, which God requires of us: or thoſe comforts, which he is pleaſed to allow us) but intenſively: It muſt be our chiefeſt aim and ſcope in our whole Life: It muſt have the preheminence before all other buſineſs, and requires our greateſt care. All we do,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.31.</note> ought to be referred to the glory of God in our Salvation. So that though we have many ſhafts to ſhoot, yet but one mark; many Offices to diſcharge, yet but one aim in them all. As all the Springs diſcharge their ſeveral
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106528:6"/>Streams through the proper Channels of their reſpective Rivers, into one Ocean; So a Chriſtians diverſe duties tend all to the ſame Savation. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, that even worldly affairs are to be mannaged with an heavenly mind. It was an excellent Moral ſaying of one, which may be well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to our purpoſe;</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">Quicquid agis, prudenter agas; &amp; reſpice finem.</q>
            <q xml:lang="eng">
               <l>What e're thou haſt to do, do prudently;</l>
               <l>And let the End be ever in thine eye.</l>
            </q>
            <p>This point ſhould be the Center, in which all our actions meet. <hi>Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus vitae Chriſtus,</hi> was the Symbol of that worthy Emperour <hi>Jovinian;</hi> and ſhould be the reſolution of every one that is called Chriſtian. Otherwiſe, if we neglect this <hi>one,</hi> all other our moſt plauſible actions, are but (as St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſpeaks of the vertues of the Heathens) <hi>ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dida peccata,</hi> glorious ſins. Since (as he diſputes againſt the <hi>Pelagians</hi>) Vertues are not diſtinguiſhed from Vices,<note place="margin">Non officiis ſed finibus a vitiis diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernondae ſunt virtutes.—Non acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſed fin bus penſantur officia <hi>Aug. contr. Julian.</hi> lib. 4 cap. 3. Quid vobis cum virtutibus, qui Dei virtutem Chiſtum ignoratis? <hi>Bern. Serm.</hi> 23. <hi>ſup. Cantica</hi>
               </note> ſo much by their Acts, as by the End for which they are done. Likewiſe St. <hi>Bernard</hi> upon the ſame account, tells the moſt accurate Moraliſts, and exacteſt Philoſophers; that they had nothing to do with Vertue, being ignorant of Chriſt, who is <hi>Virtus Dei,</hi> the power of God (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24.) For without him we can do nothing, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.5.</p>
            <p>We ſee then, that this <hi>thing</hi> is ſo <hi>one,</hi> that it is <hi>All;</hi> and that <hi>all</hi> things without this <hi>one thing,</hi> are Nothing.</p>
            <p n="3">III. This <hi>one thing</hi> is ſaid to be needful,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Unum eſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium.</note> or (as the vulgar <hi>Latine</hi> hath it) neceſſary.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In it ſelf conſidered, it is ſimply and abſolutely neceſſary; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which it is impoſſible to be happy. For our happineſs conſiſts in the full and compleat enjoyment of God, which cannot be without real communion with him; nor can we have any communion with him, but in conformity to his Will. So that we muſt be holy here, or elſe we can never be happy hereafter: Nor can we attain to holineſs, ſo as to walk with God, but in his own way.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Divine Ordination alſo confers a double neceſſity upon this <hi>one thing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Neceſſitas Praecepti. M c. 6.8. Lu. 10.25, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Mar. 10 17, <hi>&amp;c</hi> Heb. 5.9. and 11.6. and 12.28. 2 Pet. 3.14. Rom. 2.7, 10.</note> viz.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Of the Precept, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.12, 13. requiring us to fear the Lord our God, to walk in his waies, to love and ſerve him with all our heart and ſoul, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is not left to our choice, to deviſe any other way, than he hath appointed. Heaven is entailed upon thoſe only, that obey, and diligently wait upon the ſervice of God, and that patiently continue in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106528:6"/>well doing. We deceive our ſelves, if we think to come in Heaven any other way, than that which he hath preſcribed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another neceſſity is of the Means,<note place="margin">Neceſſitas medii. Acts 4.12. John 1.12. Rom 10.14.</note> whereby Eternal Life is obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Salvation were utterly unattainable by loſt man, if Chriſt had not purchaſed it for him: nor can we partake of his purchaſe, unleſs we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him; nor can we receive him, but by Faith; neither can we believe what we have no knowledge of; nor can we know except we be taught. We muſt ſome waies learn, what we can believe.</p>
            <p>Oh! how neceſſary is this word of Faith?<note place="margin">Rom. 10 8.</note> which is <hi>Mary</hi>'s preſent buſineſs, to receive from the mouth of him, who is the Word (<hi>Joh.</hi> 1.1.) that ſhe may be taught the Word of Life by him, <hi>Who is the way, and the truth, and the Life,</hi> Joh. 14.6.</p>
            <p>In which Word St. <hi>Bernard</hi> obſerves ſeven neceſſities.<note place="margin">Non ambigo eſſe plures, &amp; alias, ſed hae interim occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt. <hi>Bern. Serm.</hi> 85 ſuper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cantica. Pſalm 36.9. Epheſ. 1.8. Pſal. 119.104 Cant. 8.5. 1 Cor. 1.24.</note> Not but that there be more; but he only mentions thoſe which came to mind. The Soul (ſaith he) ſeeks this Word,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Cui conſentiat ad correctionem:</hi> that by divine admonition, the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquities of our converſation may be reformed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.9.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Quo illuminetur ad cognitionem;</hi> that in his light, we may ſee light; whereby the eyes of our underſtanding being enlightned, we may come to know God, our ſelves, and our Duty.</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Cui innitatur ad virtutem;</hi> that leaning upon Him, who is the power of God; we may be able to reſiſt temptation, and overcome all the difficulties, we ſhall find in the way to happineſs.<note place="margin">Ro. 8.35, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> So that nothing ſhall be able to ſeparate us from the Love of God.</item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Quo reformetur ad ſapientiam;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſalm 19.12.</note> that the errours of our judgements may be corrected by his inſtruction.</item>
                  <item>5. <hi>Cui conformetur ad decorem;</hi> that obſerving his direction,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.21. Phil. 2.5, 15, &amp;c.</note> and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing his example, we may live blameleſly, and without offence.</item>
                  <item>6. <hi>Cui maritetur ad foecunditatem;</hi> (ſo he expreſſeth himſelf;) that the faithful ſoul being as it were married to this Word,<note place="margin">Col. 1.10. 1 Cor. 15.58.</note> may become fruitful unto every good work, ſo as to abound in them.</item>
                  <item>7. <hi>Quo fruatur ad jucunditatem;</hi> that taſting of this ſweetneſs, we may with aſſured comfort paſs through all the ſorrows,<note place="margin">Pſalm 23.3.5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.3. Rom. 12.12. 1 Pet. 1.8.</note> and tryals which here abide us, and in the midſt of all our fears and griefs, may yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the Lord, with joy unſpeakable, and full of glory.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> was ſo ſenſible of this, that he overlooks all other things, and urgeth the Lord in his moſt earneſt Prayers, to grant him this <hi>one thing,</hi> Pſal. 27.4. <hi>One thing have I deſired of the Lord; that will I ſeek after; that I may dwell in the houſe of the Lord all the daies of my Life,</hi> &amp;c. His deſire was to make this <hi>one thing</hi> his chiefeſt buſineſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.5. <hi>My Soul, wait thou only upon God.</hi> Hence his earneſt longing to be at that Work, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.1, 2. <hi>As the Hart panteth after the water Brooks, ſo panteth my Soul after thee, O God. My Soul thirſteth for God, for the living God; when ſhall I come and appear before God?</hi> He was ſo exceedingly raviſhed with the Glory, and heavenly ſweetneſs of that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106528:7"/>employment;<note place="margin">Pſa. 84.1 2, 10. <hi>Vid Molier.</hi> in Pſal. 84.</note> that he eſteemed one day ſo ſpent, better than a thouſand otherwiſe; and preferred the meaneſt Office in this attendance, before the greateſt pleaſures, in the Tents of ſuch as regarded not Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, notwithſtanding all the gallantry and bravery of their habitations, together with all the ſolace and pleaſure of their carnal employments.</p>
            <p>Thus much concerning this <hi>one thing,</hi> and the neceſſity thereof. Now we ſhall draw ſome Inferences from what we have ſo explained.</p>
            <div n="1" type="application">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> We learn hence, that <hi>other things</hi> are not ſo neceſſary, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the World judgeth either of <hi>this</hi> or <hi>them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. There is not ſo great need of <hi>them</hi> as of <hi>this;</hi> they are needful in their kind, and place; God having ordained them for the comfort of this Life, in their ſeveral uſes. But this is indiſpenſably neceſſary to the attainment of everlaſting happineſs; <hi>as without which no man ſhall ever ſee God.</hi> We may reach Heaven without Riches, or Honour, or Applauſe of men,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.14.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yea without Health, or bodily Strength, or Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but never without Holineſs, and attendance upon Gods Service.</p>
               <p>Whilſt we ſojourn here below, we have a little need of theſe <hi>ſubſidia,</hi> or helps requiſite to the ſupport of our outward man. But, O that we did not ſo dote on them, as if they were the <hi>unum neceſſarium.</hi> By which prepoſterous acting we make our Life more cumberſome here, and prevent the enjoyment of everlaſting Life, by troubling our ſelves too much about theſe many things, and neglecting <hi>this one.</hi> Well did that Heathen diſcern the non-neceſſity of theſe many things, which diſtract the minds of men; could he but as well have known that <hi>one thing,</hi> which is ſo neceſſary. That is near-hand (ſaith he) which might ſerve turn;<note place="margin">Ad manum eſt quod ſatis eſt, ad ſupervacua ſudatur. <hi>Senec. Epiſt.</hi> 4.</note> all our toyl and ſweat is for that, which is ſuperfluous. Thoſe Stars, whoſe light is not only pleaſant, but uſeful in the Suns ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, diſappear at his return. Surely, if we were more near the Raies of the Sun of Righteouſneſs, we ſhould not be ſo much taken with the glimmerings of theſe leſſer comforts.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But that which is alſo very conſiderable; if we cordially chooſe this <hi>one thing,</hi> we ſhall be ſure to have our part of thoſe other <hi>things,</hi> (which worldlings ſo much prize,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.33. Rom. 8.32. Pſalm 34.10.</note>) in our proportion, as our heavenly Father ſees needful for us. <hi>For they that ſeek the Lord, ſhall not want any good thing.</hi> This is the moſt compendious way, to attain the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree of contentment, which only makes a man what he would be.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="application">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe 2.</head>
               <p>How much then are they to blame, who take no care for this <hi>one</hi> need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>thing?</hi> whoſe whole time is employed in making proviſion for the fleſh,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.14.12.2.</note> to fulfill the luſts thereof; and in conforming themſelves to this
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106528:7"/>preſent evil world, which lyeth wholly in wickedneſs:<note place="margin">1 Joh. 5.19. Phil. 3.19.</note> 
                  <hi>whoſe God is their Belly, whoſe glory is in their ſhame, who mind earthly things.</hi> Their inward thought is, how to make themſelves great in Wealth, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, to enjoy, and fulfill all their pleaſure. And whilſt they proſper in their way, and all things ſucceed to their deſires, they bleſs themſelves, and other men praiſe and flatter them,<note place="margin">Pſalm 49.18.</note> as if they were the only wiſe and prudent men in the world, who beſt know how to do well to themſelves. But whilſt they reject the Word of the Lord, what wiſdom is in them?<note place="margin">Jer. 8.9.</note> Surely no other than that which is declared not to deſcend from above, but is earthly, ſenſual, deviliſh: that which is enmity againſt God;<note place="margin">James 3.15. Rom. 8.7. Jer. 4 22.</note> which is only to do evil, but to do good hath no knowledge. The ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt iſſue of all their deſigns, and practice is, to prove themſelves Fools (as he was rightly called, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.26.) For what can all this profit them, when their Soul ſhall be required of them? Are not they fools, who with ſo great eagerneſs purſue their own undoing, rejecting this <hi>one thing,</hi> which is ſo neceſſary to their Salvation? They ſurfeit upon the pleaſures of this Life, and nauſeate the ſervice of God; ſaying unto him,<note place="margin">Job 21.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Depart from us, for we deſire not the knowledge of thy waies.</hi> Finding neither carnal pleaſure, nor profit in Religion, they are wholly averſe from it; ſaying, <hi>It is vain to ſerve God;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mal. 3.14. Job 21.15.</note> 
                  <hi>and what profit is it that we have kept his Ordinance? And what profit ſhould we have, if we pray unto him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus whilſt they like not to retain God in their knowledge,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.28. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 1 Tim: 1.19.4.2. Epheſ. 4.19. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> they are juſtly given up to a reprobate mind, void of all judgement. So that they do not only make Shipwrack of a good conſcience, which being cauterized, and ſeared, is become dedolent, and paſt feeling: yea they proceed ſo far at laſt, as to draw black Lines upon that very<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Rom. 2.15. Epheſ. 4.18.2.12.</note> Regiſter of natural Principles, which God had written in their hearts: whereby they become utterly alienated from the Life of God, without Chriſt, Aliens, Strangers, Hopeleſs, and Atheiſts, without God in the world. Whatever eſteem theſe may have among men; yet with all their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Pſalm 49.26.</note> ſince they underſtand not (being not acquainted with this <hi>one thing</hi>) they are no better than the Beaſts that periſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="application">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe 3.</head>
               <p>But oh! Let it be our care to make ſure of this <hi>one thing,</hi> which is ſo neceſſary. Trifle away no more precious time: let that ſuffice which is ſpent already upon the vain pleaſures, and follies,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.3.</note> and gayties of the world, whilſt we have neglected this <hi>one thing:</hi> eſpecially laying to heart theſe few conſiderations.</p>
               <p n="1">1. How ſhort and uncertain the time is,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.29. James 4.14. Epheſ. 5.16. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> which we have before us. It would be our beſt husbandry now to redeem the time, and make the beſt advantage of our preſent opportunity. Let not that bargain ſlip out of our hands: though it be purchaſed with the loſs of thoſe former de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights and pleaſures, which we have ſo hotly purſued; but could never gain
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106528:8"/>any true comfort,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.9. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> or ſatisfaction from them: but contrarily they drown, and plunge us in deſtruction, and perdition.</p>
               <p n="2">2. What if God ſhould call thee to an account in that preſent ſtate, and poſture in which thou now art? This muſt certainly be called for; and the time is at hand,<note place="margin">Luke 16.2.</note> when thou muſt be no longer Steward; when thou muſt give a ſtrict account, what thou haſt done with each Talent, wherewith thou haſt been truſted: how thou haſt ſpent thy time, and ſtate, and ſtrength, and gifts: what progreſs thou haſt made in this <hi>one neceſſary thing.</hi> O let the conſcience of thy negligence hitherto, and of thy preſent poverty,<note place="margin">Rev. 3.17.</note> blindneſs, and nakedneſs (ſo occaſioned) move thee to conſider, how thou maiſt provide for that great account, that thou maiſt give it with joy, and not with grief.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Conſider thy happineſs, if when the Lord comes, he find thee ſo employed.<note place="margin">Luke 12.43.</note> Then ſhalt thou be bleſſed; as our Saviour promiſeth. But with what face wilt thou look upon him, if his coming find thee idle, as to this <hi>one thing,</hi> and only buſied in worldly employments, or poſſibly in the ſervice of Satan, and Sin?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Conſider, that none of thoſe other many things, which have been ſo eagerly ſought after (how ever glorious in the eyes of the world, or in thy own deceived judgement) can ſtead thee at all in that day, if thou wanteſt this.</p>
               <p>That man whoſe attainments were ſo conſiderable, and the care of his converſation ſo exact,<note place="margin">Mark 10.17.18, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> that our Saviour is ſaid to love him; who alſo had great poſſeſſions: yet could not with all theſe come into a capacity of Heaven and Eternal Life, for want of this. O, how many, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe compleat men, come ſhort of Heaven, for lack of this? Can any man perſwade his own reaſon, that Wealth, Honour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or any of thoſe <hi>Excelſa mundi,</hi> thoſe ſo much admired things of the World can intitle him to Heaven? or that his wit, parts, learning, or carnal wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom can make him acceptable in the ſight of God? or that his moral and innocent deportment among men, ſhould procure his everlaſting happineſs without this <hi>one thing?</hi> Surely then no Rich, nor Prudent, nor meerly Moral man ſhould ever come into Hell. Then ſhould Heaven and Eternal Glory be as obvious to Pagans, Turks, and other Infidels, as to true Believers. Then had our Saviour in vain told his Diſciples, that the way to Heaven was ſo ſtrait,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.14. Luke 13.24. Mark 16.16. John 3.18.</note> that there be but few that find it; and that <hi>many ſhall ſtrive to enter in, and ſhall not be able:</hi> in vain had he ſaid, that <hi>he who believeth not, is condemned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Conſider, that this <hi>one</hi> is the <hi>only thing</hi> which ſhall never fail, when all the glory of the World ſhall paſs away:<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.24, 25. 1 John 2.17.</note> when the friendſhip of the world ſhall ſtand thee in no ſtead. But of this afterwards.</p>
               <p>Having now done with the firſt part of the Text, <hi>viz.</hi> our Saviours Admonition to <hi>Martha;</hi> we come to ſpeak of the ſecond part, <hi>viz.</hi> the Commendation of <hi>Mary.</hi> Where we ſhall conſider,</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:106528:8"/>
               <p n="1">1. The Party commended, <hi>Mary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>thing</hi> for which ſhe is commended, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe ſhe made choice of <hi>that good part,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="1">I. The Party commended is deſcribed,</p>
               <p n="1">1. In the Text, by her Name, <hi>Mary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The Context compared with ſome other places, that make menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of her, will give us ſome light concerning her condition.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Mary</hi> is a Name renowned in Scripture. No one Name affords more plenty of good Souls regiſtred in holy writ, than this. There we read of many and excellent <hi>Mary</hi>'s.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Mary,</hi> or <hi>Miriam</hi> (all is one) the Siſter of <hi>Moſes:</hi> who was inſtrumental in bringing the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> out of <hi>Egypt;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Micah 6.4. Exod. 15.20.</note> and was moſt active in praiſing God for that deliverance.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Mary</hi> the Mother of our Lord, ſaluted by the Angel,<note place="margin">Luke 1.28.</note> the favorite of Heaven, and bleſſed among Women; of the Blood Royal, of the houſe of <hi>David;</hi> admirably devout;<note place="margin">verſe 46, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2.14, 51. John 19 25. Acts 1.14. Luke 2.35.</note> a great hoarder of heavenly trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; ſhe abode by the Lord at his Death, and with his Church after his Aſcenſion; was much vers'd in Affliction, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as was foretold by holy <hi>Simeon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. This <hi>Mary</hi> in the Text;<note place="margin">It is vulgarly taken for granted (eſpecially in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>) that this <hi>Mary,</hi> and <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> are both one, and alſo the ſame with that Woman, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.37 who was a ſinner. But this opinion is vehemently oppoſed, and refuted by diverſe learned men amongſt them, eſpecially by <hi>Faber Stapulenſ.</hi> and <hi>Jod Clictoveus,</hi> and ſince by the Jeſuit <hi>Salmeron,</hi> in <hi>Luc.</hi> 7. of which ſee an account in <hi>Gerh. Harm. c.</hi> 143. Alſo <hi>Vid. Lyſer. Har. c.</hi> 58. <hi>Janſen. Conc. Evang. c.</hi> 55. <hi>Came<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ar.</hi> in <hi>John</hi> 11.1.</note> of whom hereafter.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> out of whom Chriſt caſt ſeven Devils, <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.2. A zealous follower of Chriſt, and who adminiſtred to him of her ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.2. Diligent in attending upon the Croſs, and Sepulcher of Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.56, 61. and 28.1. <hi>Mar.</hi> 15.47. To whom our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour firſt appeared after his Reſurrection, <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.14. which ſhe alſo, by his appointment, carefully reports to his Diſciples, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 18.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Mary</hi> the Mother of <hi>James</hi> and <hi>Joſes;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The fifth and ſixth <hi>Mary</hi>'s alſo are taken for one and the ſame by <hi>Janſ. Conc. Evang. cap.</hi> 143. and <hi>Gerh. Harm. de Reſur. cap.</hi> 1. <hi>St. Hieron.</hi> is uncertain, <hi>Contr. Helv. cap.</hi> 7. <hi>&amp; Ep.</hi> 150 q—4. But <hi>Joh.</hi> 19.25. They are diſtinct in moſt Greek Copies, as alſo in our Tranſlation, and <hi>Lat. Arab.</hi> and <hi>Eth.</hi> more clearly in the <hi>Syria<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>k,</hi> and <hi>Perſian,</hi> by a <hi>copula.</hi> So likewiſe doth <hi>Aretius</hi> render it.</note> who with</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Mary</hi> the Wife of <hi>Cleophas,</hi> waited upon the Croſs of Chriſt, (and doubtleſs were alſo of thoſe that prepared Spices and Ointments to anoint his Body, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.1. <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.1.) <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.56. <hi>Joh.</hi> 19.25.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Mary</hi> the Mother of <hi>John Mark;</hi> whoſe Houſe was the recepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the Church, <hi>Act.</hi> 12.12.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Another <hi>Mary</hi> is mentioned by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> with this commendation; that ſhe beſtowed much labour upon the Saints, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.6.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:106528:9"/>
               <p>So many gracious and excellent Women we find in Scripture called by this Name.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. As for her condition: ſhe is is here ſaid to be the Siſter of <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> and <hi>Martha</hi> (compared with <hi>J h.</hi> 11.) How religiouſly affected ſhe was, appears by this Context. She is ſuppoſed to be of Noble ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction; and it is manifeſt by this place, that they were very wealthy, by their liberal and frequent entertainment of Chriſt and his Diſciples, and by the great and ſudden proviſion they made for him, which at this time filled <hi>Martha</hi>'s hands ſo full of buſineſs. And that they were of ſpecial note,<note place="margin">Calv. Lyſer, Janſca. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in loc.</note> may appear by the great concourſe of ſo many of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who came in to comfort the two Siſters, at the Death of <hi>Lazarus, Joh.</hi> 11.19. How much ſhe was in favour with Chriſt, and beloved by him, appeared by his frequent viſits, and turning in thither.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">— Rarae fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant felicibus arae.</note>It hath ever been accounted rare, to find ſo much devotion, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious care in Perſons that are Rich, Great, and Eminent in the World.</p>
               <p>But we here ſee this <hi>Mary</hi> ſo careful of her Souls benefit, that ſhe caſts off all other buſineſs, to attend only on this <hi>one,</hi> ſitting at Jeſus feet to hear his Word.</p>
               <p>Our Saviour ſaith, <hi>That a Rich man ſhall hardly enter into the Kingdom of Heaven:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 19.23, 24.</note> 
                  <hi>and that it is eaſier for a Camel to go through the eye of a Needle,</hi> &amp;c. And verily there is great reaſon why it muſt be ſo. Since Rich men of all others are moſt expoſed to temptations,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.9. Mat. 13.22.</note> and ſnares. There is a deceitfulneſs in Riches, which meeting with a deceitful, and deſperately wicked heart eaſily prevails, to make ſuch a man inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal to undo both himſelf and others.<note place="margin">Jer. 17.9.</note> For,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">Certe enim multa peccata videntur ad Divites perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere. Quum enim plus agunt, &amp; plus mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrant, &amp; plus ad eos pendet res familiaris ampla; dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficile eſt, ut non plura peccata con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trahant. <hi>Aug.</hi> in Pſal. 132. Pſalm. 2.3. Jer. 5.5.</note>1. He hath power to execute, what ever his naughty heart deſires to do. <hi>Quicquid libet, licet.</hi> He ſcorns to be controll'd, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12.4. who have ſaid, <hi>With our tongue we will prevail, who is Lord over us? We have power in our hand, to enforce obedience to our Orders: if we ſay it, who dare gainſay it?</hi> Their Motto is, <hi>Sic volo, ſic jubeo:</hi> and who may diſpute their commands? They have enough to maintain their Pride; to practiſe their Vices; to gratifie the Fleſh; to trample under foot their reprovers, and remove out of the way, what ever may give check to their proceedings. What care they for the Law and Commands of God? They are reſolved to break thoſe bonds in ſunder, and caſt away thoſe cords from them.</p>
               <p>When the Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> had conſidered the ſtate of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and ſaw the Commonalty ſo rude and incorrigible; he imputed it to their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, which for want of breeding, and converſe with the more civil and refined ſort of men, rendred them utterly ignorant of, and unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the waies of the Lord. But he hoped to find ſome better entertainment of his errand among the great ones: who by reaſon of their advantage of education, and converſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> could not be ignorant of ſuch things as they were moſt concerned to know. <hi>But theſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>have altogether broken the yoke, and burſt the bonds.</hi> They were
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106528:9"/>grown ſuch ſons of <hi>Belial</hi> (as they ſaid of <hi>Nabal,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Belial</hi> i.e. abſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> jugo. Quod de collo ſuo Dei abjecerint ſervitutem. <hi>Hier.</hi> lib. 2. in Eph. 4. He derives it from <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> abſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> jugum.</note> 1 Sam. 25.17.) that he could not ſpeak to them. Men that could not endure the yoke of any wholſome Law or diſcipline; or the curb of a Reproof, or Admonition.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But as they have power to do what they liſt; ſo they want not friends to juſtifie their miſdoings; nor fordid flatterers to ſooth them in their wickedneſs, nor companions to excite, and provoke them to evil; nor inſtruments to gratifie their luſts, and act their pleaſure.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They are out of the reach of thoſe, that cordially deſire their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. Inferiours are diſdained;<note place="margin">Heb. 13.17.</note> and their faithful Paſtors (who ſtand charged with the care of their Souls, and at whoſe hands their blood will be required,<note place="margin">Ezek. 3.18. Amos 5.10. Jer. 18.18.43.2.20.8, 10. 2 Chron. 36.16. Jer. 11.21.</note> if they connive at their ſins) if they diſcharge their duty, are ſure to meet with ſuch entertainment, as the Prophets of old had, <hi>viz.</hi> hatred, contempt, contumelie, and perſecution. Theſe are ſuch, as neither fearing God, nor regarding man, dare ſay to the Prophets, <hi>Propheſie not unto us right things; ſpeak unto us ſmooth things,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Get you out of the way,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Cauſe the holy one of Iſrael to ceaſe from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us,</hi> Iſa. 30.10, 11.</p>
               <p>But what ſpeak I of ſuch wicked perſons, whoſe tranſgreſſions declare them ſuch as <hi>have not the fear of God before their eyes;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm 36.1.</note> when Riches and worldly advantages have ſuch a bad influence upon the beſt hearts, being ſuch incentives to their remaining corruptions?<note place="margin">Pſalm 30.6. Read the like of <hi>Hezekiah.</hi> 2 Chron. 32.23, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Mat. 6.29.20.21.</note> Even <hi>David</hi> was too prone to be exalted in his proſperity, and upon account of his greatneſs did greatly offend; as is diverſly recorded in his ſtory. It is a rare thing to find proſperity humble, or devout. Men grow too careleſs of Heaven, when they have ſo much treaſure laid up on Earth. Beſides, it is the unhappineſs of rich men (though they be good) that either they have none to reprove them; or elſe through paſſion, and height of Spirit (in conceit of their diſtance) they cannot, or will not bear a reproof. If <hi>Jeſurun</hi> wax fat, he will kick.<note place="margin">Deut. 32.15. 1 Cor. 1.26. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Well therefore might the Apoſtle conclude; not many (Rich or) mighty men of power, nor Noble (or well-born) are called.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="application">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe <hi>1.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Oh what need then have great and rich men to keep their hearts with all diligence, that they be not enſnared with the deceitfulneſs of Riches,<note place="margin">Prov. 4.23.</note> ſo as to neglect their <hi>better part?</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> well knew their danger, when he required <hi>Timothy</hi> to charge them, <hi>That they be not high minded,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.17, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>nor truſt in uncertain Riches,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But to lay up for themſelves a good foundation for the time to come, laying bold on Eternal Life.</hi> According to this, is our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours ferious admonition;<note place="margin">Luke 16.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Make to your ſelves friends of the Mammon of unrighteouſneſs, that when you fail, they may receive you into everlaſting
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106528:10"/>habitations.</hi> He teacheth how to make the beſt advantage of the unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Mammon;</hi> and to convert thoſe occaſions of ſin to contrary purpoſe; that the good uſe of our Riches may procure us friends and favour, when we ſhall ſtand in greateſt need.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="application">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe <hi>2.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Nevertheleſs, though there be but few great and Rich men, that mind the things of God, and make a right uſe of their worldly advantages: yet (bleſſed be God) there are ſome ſuch. And O how are ſuch men bound to praiſe God, and we for them! that he hath given them (to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with their Riches and Honour) an holy, humble, tractable, gracious Spirit, truly deſirous to ſerve him, improving each opportunity (as <hi>Mary</hi> here) for the advancement of their everlaſting Salvation: preferring in their moſt deliberate choice this <hi>one thing</hi> neceſſary, before all the pleaſures, and treaſures in the World. Whoſe Riches are helps to fruitfulneſs in works of mercy;<note place="margin">Heb. 13.16.</note> 
                  <hi>who forget not to do good, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, knowing that with ſuch Sacrifices God is well pleaſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh how lovely, and pleaſant a thing is it, to ſee a great and Noble Perſon ſerious and devout in the ſervice of God? Who with Royal Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>David</hi> hath learned to prefer the true and ſincere ſerving of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all his Riches and Honours;<note place="margin">Pſ. 119.14, 72.</note> and to ſet more by the divine favour, than all that good,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 4 6, 7.63.3. Pſa. 26.4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 119.115. Pſalm 1.1, 2.</note> which worldings ſo buſily enquire after, yea, than Life it ſelf. Therefore with that religious King, he will not converſe with vain perſons, but caſheers all wicked company, that he may attend upon heavenly employments: eſteeming him only bleſſed, <hi>Who walks not in the counſel of the ungodly, nor ſtands in the way of ſinners, nor ſits in the ſeat of the ſcornful; but delights in the Law of God, and makes it bis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual meditation.</hi> Such are bleſſed men indeed: who, as they provide well for their own ſure peace and comfort; ſo are they publick bleſſings to all their Relations, and to whomſoever elſe have the happineſs of converſe with them: whilſt the light of the holy converſation becomes more conſpicuous, and ſo more exemplary, by the advantage of that height wherein Providence hath placed them. Like benigne Planets, their influence cheareth all within their reach. How uſeful are ſuch men both to Church and Common-wealth? They ſtudy the proſperity of <hi>Sion,</hi> which they prefer before their chief joy.<note place="margin">Pſalm 137.6. Job 31.16.</note> And their care is with <hi>Job</hi> to gratifie the deſire, and anſwer the hope of the needy, to feed the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, and cloath the naked, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe mens practice, and priviledges you may ſee lively deſcribed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112. <hi>per totum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hitherto we have conſidered the party thus deſcribed. It remains to ſpeak of the <hi>Thing,</hi> for which ſhe is commended. Where we have,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Her Act, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ſhe hath choſen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The Object, or <hi>thing choſen,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>that good part.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">I. For the firſt: Choice ſuppoſeth two or more things, or waies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106528:10"/>to a mans diſcretion, of which he takes that which pleaſeth him beſt. The rational man can prefer nothing in choice,<note place="margin">Electio eſt melioris ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptatio.</note> but <hi>ſub ratione boni;</hi> and would not miſs in it, if the rectitude of the judgement were not vitiated. As ſome diſtempered Bodies refuſe good meat, to feed on Aſhes, Coals, or Gravel: which is not properly the fault of the Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, but occaſioned by the prevailing diſtemper. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> guided by their Luſt, loathed <hi>Manna,</hi> and luſted after the Fleſh-pots, and the Onions, and Garlick of <hi>Egypt.</hi> Yea, even gracious ſouls,<note place="margin">Num. 11 5.6.</note> through mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, do oft miſchooſe. Thus <hi>Lot</hi> beholding the pleaſantneſs of the plain of <hi>Jordan,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 13 9. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> choſe <hi>Sodom</hi> for his Habitation.</p>
               <p>God puts man to his choice: he ſets him, as it were in <hi>Bivio</hi> (as the Antients feigned of <hi>Hercules</hi>) to chooſe which way he pleaſeth. <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 30.15.</note> 
                  <hi>I have ſet before thee this day, Life and Good, and Death and Evil.</hi> Here men make a different choice, as they ſtand affected.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Thoſe that fear God, and conſult their own eternal welfare, chooſe the good, and refuſe the evil. Such was <hi>David</hi>'s choice;<note place="margin">Pſalm 84.10.</note> 
                  <hi>I had rather</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>be a door-keeper in the houſe of my God,</hi> &amp;c. How oft doth he record this choice in <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119?<note place="margin">Pſalm 119.13, 14.30, 36, 37, 72, 97, 173. &amp; alibi. <hi>Joſeph. Anti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Jud.</hi> l. 2. c. 5.</note> which ſhews how exceedingly he was pleaſed with it, and with the very thoughts of it. Such was <hi>Moſes</hi>'s choice: who being adopted by <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Daughter and Heir, that had deſigned him for her Heir, and Succeſſor to the Kingdom (if we may believe <hi>Joſephus</hi>) yet refuſed all that Honour, and grandeur, and the appendant Riches and Pleaſures,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.24, 25, 26.</note> to embrace the hardeſt lot of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, Affliction and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eproach; having reſpect unto the (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) recompence of reward. This was the commendation of thoſe Eunuchs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.4. that they did chooſe the things that pleaſed God: let men be pleaſed or diſpleaſed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But the wicked hate knowledge,<note place="margin">Prov. 1.22, 29. Iſa. 65 12. and 66.4.</note> and do not chooſe the fear of the Lord. They do evil before his eyes, and chooſe that, wherein he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth not: but chooſe their own waies, and their ſoul delighteth in their abominations. One would think it was impoſſible, that men in their wits ſhould refuſe everlaſting Happineſs, for momentary and ſinful pleaſures: but our daily experience makes it manifeſt.<note place="margin">Pro. 1.22, 32. and 12.15. and 17.16. Pſalm 94.8. Jude 10.</note> Therefore the Scripture juſtly calls ſuch men Fools, Bruits, and mad men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who wilfully refuſe the paths of life, and deſperately ruſh upon their ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ruine.</p>
               <p>But God gives more grace to his children; who following the guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of his Spirit, with <hi>Mary</hi> make choice of this <hi>good part</hi> upon beſt conſideration: For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. They are ſenſible of their own need. They know they are ſick,<note place="margin">Mat. 9.12. Pſ. 109.24, 26. Rev. 3.17, 18.</note> and ſtand in need of Medicine; weak, and need ſupport: they know they are wretched and miſerable, and poor, and blind, and naked: and therefore make haſt to Chriſt for ſpiritual riches, and heavenly grace (whereof he hath an inexhauſtible ſtore, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.8.) to enrich them; for eye ſalve of divine knowledge (from his plenitude,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106528:11"/>
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 2.2,<note place="margin">Eph. 1 17, 18. Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 3.9.</note> 3.) to illuminate them; for the robe of his righteouſneſs, to cover their nakedneſs. Neceſſity enforceth them (as the Prodigal, <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.17, &amp;c.) to go to him for relief; who ſo lovingly invites them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28. and is ready <hi>ebviis ulnis,</hi> with ſpread arms to embrace them. Therefore they refuſe the evil, and chooſe the good, ſeeing the inevitable deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the one, and aſſured comfort in the other.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They ſee and acknowledge the glorious excellency of holineſs, and heavenly practiſe: how excellent it is in it ſelf, being the lively Image of the moſt holy God;<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4 24. 2 Pet. 1.4.</note> whereby they are made partakers of the divine nature. As alſo the ſweetneſs and comfort of its exerciſe: whereby they have communion with God, converſing and walking with him (as <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Noah</hi> did,<note place="margin">Mic. 6.5. Gal. 5.25. Rom. 8.1. and 6.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.22. and 6.9.) in and after the Spirit, in newneſs of Life, having their converſation in Heaven, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20. As Children of Light, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.8. <hi>David</hi> ſeeing this, prefers one day ſo ſpent before a thouſand otherwiſe.<note place="margin">Pſalm 84.10.</note> Indeed one hours ſweet enjoyment of God, gives the Soul more ſatisfaction, than all the pleaſures of the world can give:<note place="margin">Pſa. 119.14, 72. Phil. 3.7, 8.</note> and is therefore to be choſen rather than all Riches. Chriſt alone (who is only thus enjoyed) is to be preferred before all gain. And every wiſe Merchant, who trades for Heaven, will ſell all, to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe this Pearl.<note place="margin">Mat. 13.45, 46.</note>
               </p>
               <p>To enlarge upon this Subject, would ſoon exceed the intended limits of this Diſcourſe. Therefore I ſhall only intimate this further: that the way of holineſs is the high way to everlaſting happineſs (which is but Holineſs perfected in Glory) <hi>For without holineſs no man ſhall ever ſee God:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12.14 Mat. 5.8. Pſ. 15. and 24.</note> ſince that beatifical Viſion is reſerved for them only, who are <hi>pure in heart,</hi> and Life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="application">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe <hi>1.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Oh then, how ill do thoſe men provide for their immortal Souls; who either wilfully refuſe what <hi>Mary</hi> choſe; or make a bad choice of ſuch things, as are either hurtful, or at leaſt unprofitable; or that only pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to make this good choice, but do not; or that relinquiſh (after ſuch profeſſion) what they ſeemed to chooſe?</p>
               <p n="1">1. How many are there, who enjoy the precious opportunities of this Word,<note place="margin">Heb. 2.3.</note> ſo conſtantly Preached amongſt them, and yet <hi>neglect ſo great ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation;</hi> making light of the Lords earneſt invitation (as thoſe recuſants, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.5.) who refuſe,<note place="margin">Prov. 1.24, 25, 29. Iſa. 65.2.</note> when he calls, and when he ſtretcheth forth his hand, regard it not; who ſet at nought all his counſel, and will none of his reproof; but hate knowledge, and will not chooſe the fear of the Lord? Theſe men put away the Word of God from them; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by declaring that they judge themſelves unworthy of Eternal Life: whilſt they even ſay unto God,<note place="margin">Acts 13 46.</note> 
                  <hi>Depart from us, for we deſire not the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thy waies.</hi> Hating inſtruction they caſt Gods Word behind them; inſtead whereof they chooſe their own waies,<note place="margin">Job 21.14. Pſalm 50.17.</note> and their ſoul delighteth in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106528:11"/>their abominations;<note place="margin">Iſa. 66.3, 4.</note> whereby they provoke God to chooſe their deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And even as they delight not to retain the knowledge of God in their minds, it pleaſeth him to give them over to a reprobate mind,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.28. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> to do thoſe things which are moſt unſeemly and unhandſome, and quite contrary to all decency and duty.</p>
               <p>Thus it fares likewiſe with them,<note place="margin">Jer. 2.36. Judg. 5.8. 2 Tim 4 3. 1 Tim 4.1. Gal. 3.1.</note> who (in reference to Religion) gad about to change their way, with the Idolatrous <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> chooſing new Gods, new opinions, and fancies. <hi>Who having itching ears, heap to themſelves teachers after their own luſts;</hi> and whilſt they give ear to thoſe ſeducing Spirits, which bewitch them, they depart from the Faith, and do not obey the Truth. For not receiving the love of it,<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.10, &amp;c.</note> they will not believe it, but <hi>take pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs.</hi> Wherefore God in juſt judgement ſends them ſtrong deluſions, that they ſhould believe a Lie; and <hi>gives them up to uncleanneſs, through the luſts of their own hearts:</hi> Yea,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.24. Rev. 22.11. Epheſ. 4.19. Heb. 2.3.</note> 
                  <hi>they give themſelves over to laſciviouſneſs, to work all uncleanneſs with greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> Thus they receive a juſt reward of their ſlighting this <hi>good part, and neglecting ſo great ſalvation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. And although ſome of theſe wilfull refuſers do eſcape theſe groſs debaucheries; yet they are ſo far left to themſelves, as (with <hi>Demas,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4 10.) to embrace this preſent World, which lieth wholly in wickedneſs, and can afford no better thing than Luſt and Pride;<note place="margin">1 John 5.19.2.16. Cum pereunte deceptrice, &amp; ipſi pereunt. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>g.</hi> 1. Cor. 7.31. 1 Pet. 1.24. Prov. 11.7. Pſalm. 49 11. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Intima eorum viſcera.</note> to which whilſt they conform themſelves, they periſh with that periſhing cheat. For as its form, and outward appearance (it being nothing more) even all its pomp and glory periſheth, and paſſeth away, withereth, fadeth, and vaniſheth; ſo doth the worldlings hope, and expectation, even his inward thoughts, his plots, deſigns, and projects to perpetuate his Name and Inheritance in his poſterity. So that whilſt they refuſe this <hi>one thing neceſſary,</hi> they make choice of ſuch things, as are either deſtructive or unprofitable.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Neither can they eſcape this reproof, who only pretend to make choice of this <hi>good part,</hi> but do not. Who <hi>have a Form,</hi> and appearance <hi>of godlineſs, but deny the power thereof.</hi> They have a figure,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.4. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> or ſhape of holineſs, but not the ſubſtance and eſſence; uſing it only as a Vizard or Mask to cover their ſhameful deformities.<note place="margin">Mat. 23.27.</note> Our Saviour compares them to painted Sepulchres, which are gloriouſly gilded on the outſide, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly are full of all uncleanneſs. Such feign themſelves juſt men (as <hi>Luk.</hi> 20.20.) and boaſt with that Phariſee (<hi>Luk.</hi> 18.11,<note place="margin">Iſa. 65.5. Luke 16.15. Mat. 15.8. Pſalm 78.36. Hoſ. 11.12. Acts 8.21. Ezek. 14.3, 4.</note> 12.) that they are holier than others, juſtifying themſelves before men; but God knoweth their hearts; how far they are from him, when they draw near, and flatter him with their Lips, and lie unto him with their Tongues, compaſſing him about with their lies, but their heart is not right with him. For in it have they ſet up their Idols; therefore the Lord will not be enquired of by them; but will anſwer them according to the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of their Idols, and not according to their pretence. <hi>In the day when God ſhall judge the ſecrets of men, and bring to light the hidden things
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106528:12"/>of darkneſs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.5.</note> 
                  <hi>and make manifeſt the counſels of their bearts, and render to every man according to his works;</hi> then ſhall theſe pretenders be ſent away with a <hi>Non novi vos,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 7.23.</note> 
                  <hi>I know you not, depart from me, ye workers of iniquity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. But how damnable then is the condition of thoſe, that have ſeemed Religious and devout, pretending to chooſe the better part; but after all their flouriſhes have ſtarted aſide like a deceitful Bow,<note place="margin">Pſal. 78.57. and 18.21. 2 Pet. 2.22.</note> and wickedly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from their God; returning with the Dog to his vomiting again, and with the Sow that was waſhed, to her wallowing in the mire. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever theſe have ſeemed, or pretended to be; they may have had ſome ſlight taſt of the heavenly gift,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.4, 5.</note> and of the good Word of God, and of the powers of the World to come; not only their underſtandings being enlightned, but their affections alſo moved, like thoſe Temporaries, (<hi>Mat.</hi> 13.20. <hi>Mar</hi> 4.16.) who immediately receive the Word with joy,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Rev. 22.17. Pſalm 17.15. and 63.5. Rom. 15.13. 1 Pet. 1.8.</note> none more forward, nor ſooner cloſe with it than they: but they never had any deep taſt of that heavenly ſweetneſs, which the Lord vouchſafes his beloved (<hi>Cant.</hi> 5.1.) to whom he gives large draughts of his Grace and favour, to their full ſatisfaction, repleniſhing their hearts with unſpeakable joy. They have never attained that which holy <hi>David</hi> ſo paſſionately commends, (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.8.) and admires (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.103.) nor have they really experienced how gracious the Lord is.<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Let not this be Interpreted to the prejudice or diſcouragement of any poor ſoul, that hath ſincerely made choice of the Lord Jeſus as his Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, eſteeming all things ſhort of him <hi>as dung and droſs in compariſon of him;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 3.8. Pſal. 42.1. &amp; 119.38, 131.</note> who pants after him, <hi>as the Hart panteth after the water Brooks,</hi> and longs for his Commandments, and is devoted to his fear: Though he yet hath not attained ſuch ſatisfactory perceptions and experience of the divine favour, as to keep his love ſick heart from fainting, when the <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved withdraws himſelf,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant. 5.6, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>and cannot be found upon diligent ſearch,</hi> &amp;c. Thoſe conſolations are oft delayed, and this good Wine is reſerved for the laſt; this great goodneſs is laid up for all ſuch as fear God, though they for ſome time neither ſee nor feel it.<note place="margin">Pſal. 31.19.</note> He knows (though they do not) the thoughts of Peace,<note place="margin">Jer. 29.11.</note> that he thinketh towards them, and will manifeſt in his due time.</p>
               <p>But theſe who are here apprehended, are ſuch as never had any real hungring, or thirſting after Righteouſneſs: but have only for low ends ſeemed to comply with the Goſpel, and have taken up only a form of Godlineſs.<note place="margin">Pſ. 106.21, 24.</note> Therefore it is no marvel, that they ſoon forget God their Saviour, and deſpiſe the promiſed Inheritance, luſting after their former Fleſhpots, and preferring the Onions and Garlick of <hi>Egypt,</hi> before the Milk and Honey of <hi>Canaan.</hi> Having taken a few ſteps out of <hi>Sodom,</hi> the remembrance of their former pleaſures, there prevails upon them to look back (but as it was with <hi>Lots</hi> Wiſe,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.39.</note> 
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.26.) to their own perdition. Their glorious building had no better than a ſandy Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; therefore when the rain,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.26, 27. 2 Pet. 2.20, 21. Luk. 11.25, 26.</note> and floods, and wind beat upon it, it muſt needs fall. Their blaze goes out in ſtinking ſnuff, their latter end be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing worſe than the beginning.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="application">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:106528:12"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe <hi>2.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Surely then it highly concerns every man to examine himſelf, whether he hath made a ſerious choice with <hi>Mary</hi> of this <hi>good part.</hi> If we have done ſo indeed, not deceiving our ſelves,</p>
               <p n="1">1. We ſhall earneſtly deſire, and long to enjoy what we have ſo choſen (as was ſaid before) our ſouls will thirſt for God, for the living God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 42.1, 2. and 101.2.</note> and cry out with holy <hi>David, When ſhall I come and appear before God?</hi> And, <hi>O when wilt thou come unto me?</hi> So did that gracious ſoul long after the Ordinances of God (wherein only he could enjoy him, whom he ſo dearly loved) that he opened his mouth and panted,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.131. verſe 20.</note> longing for his Commandments: like one that had run himſelf out of breath, in purſuit of what he paſſionately deſireth, and ſtands in greateſt need of, ſo that he even breaks his heart with vehement ſtriving to obtain it. The long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſoul cannot be without <hi>this one neceſſary thing:</hi> it cannot brook de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lays, but preſſeth upon the Lord. <hi>How long wilt thou forget me, O Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 13.1. Quamdiu, quamdiu cras &amp; cras? Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re non modo? Quare non hac horâ? <hi>Aug. Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſ.</hi> lib. 9. cap. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>for ever? How long wilt thou hide thy face from me? How long ſhall I be put off from day to day? Why not now, Lord?</hi> ſaid St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> after the Lord had opened his eyes to diſcover, and his heart to chooſe and deſire this <hi>one thing.</hi> This choice can not ſtand with a careleſs indifferency.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We ſhall diligently and ſolicitouſly enquire after, and make uſe of all means to obtain it. That eager deſire, even now mentioned, will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force earneſtneſs in Prayer, attentiveneſs in Hearing, ſtudiouſneſs in Reading, ſeriouſneſs in Meditation. <hi>All our delight will be in the Law of the Lord, and in his Law we ſhall meditate day and night.</hi> How ſweet will the glad tidings of Salvation be to the longing Soul? How com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable to hear of joy and gladneſs, and that <hi>Peace of God which paſſeth all underſtanding,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat 7.7. Prov. 2.3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 10.4. Heb. 12.3.</note> and all thoſe ſweet breathings of the Holy Ghoſt in the Goſpel of Salvation? And theſe are the requeſts of thoſe only, that ask, and ſeek, and knock. This hid treaſure cannot be found, but by moſt diligent ſearch. It is the diligent hand, that brings in this riches. He that would partake of theſe joys, muſt not be weary,<note place="margin">Gen. 49.18.</note> nor faint in his mind, nor ſlack or take off his hand, but perſiſt with all perſeverance, even to the laſt gaſp, waiting (with good <hi>Jacob</hi>) for this Salvation.<note place="margin">J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b 23.12. Prov. 8.11. Phil. 3.8.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Such as chooſe this <hi>good part,</hi> will eſteem it according to its worth. They will ſet an higher price upon it, than any worldly treaſure. Thus <hi>Job</hi> preferred it before his neceſſary Food; <hi>David</hi> before all Riches; <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> accounts it better than Rubies, and that all the things that can be deſired, are not to be compared to it. Such a price did St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Chriſt (who is the ſubſtance of the Goſpel, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.23.) that he accounted all things but loſs, and no better than<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Unus apex do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinae, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in Gal. 5. Ego qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ſine verbo ne in Paradiſo optarim vive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re: At cum verbo etiam in Inferno facile eſt vivere. Id. in Pſal. 120.</note> Dung (or Dogs meat) that he might win Chriſt. This made <hi>Luther</hi> ſay, <hi>That one Tittle of the Word was more worth than Heaven and Earth;</hi> and that he would not wiſh to live in Paradiſe without the Word; but with it he could live in Hell
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106528:13"/>it ſelf. A ſtrange Hyperbole, but an expreſs evidence of his exceeding great affection to it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This choice is ever attended with great care, that we come not ſhort of that which we have choſen. <hi>Let us fear</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.1.) <hi>leſt any come ſhort, or be caſt behind</hi> (as he that ſets in vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly to run the Race,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> but fails before he reach the Goal). And again, we ought abundantly to heed, that we ſpill not, or ſhed the things which we have heard,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 2 John 8. Rev. 2.25.</note> 
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.1. As a riven Veſſel which loſeth the liquor pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into it. This is that which St. <hi>John</hi> adviſeth; <hi>Look to your ſelves, that we loſe not the things, which we have wrought, but that we may receive a full reward.</hi> Such was that admonition to the Church of <hi>Thiatira: That which ye have already hold faſt.</hi> He that is ſerious in his choice, will (with St. <hi>Paul</hi>) ſtretch forth to thoſe things, which are yet before, <hi>and preſs towards the mark</hi> (or ſcope) <hi>for the Prize,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 3.13, 14.</note> and grow yet more vigorous in the purſuit.<note place="margin">J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b 17.9. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The righteous ſhall hold on his way, and he that hath clean hands, ſhall add ſtrength.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus it appears, that no careleſs or ſloathful perſons, who ſet light by the Word of God; or ſuch as neglect it; or prefer the World before it; or that grudge to be at coſt or pains to attend upon it, can be ſaid to make choice with <hi>Mary</hi> of this <hi>good part.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="application">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe <hi>3.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Let us therefore take care, that <hi>Mary's Choice</hi> may be ours; conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, what hath been ſaid before, our great neceſſity of it, and the great benefit and comfort it brings with it. If we refuſe, we are undone for ever; whilſt we wilfully neglect, and reject everlaſting Happineſs, for the love of momentary, vain, and ſinful pleaſures.</p>
               <p>Behold the Lord hath brought thee before the two Mounts, <hi>Gerizim,</hi> and <hi>Ebal;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deu. 27.12, 13. Deu. 30.15, 19.</note> ſetting before thee this day Bleſſing and Curſing, Life and Good, Death and Evil. Thou haſt thy choice: conſider what thou haſt to do, whether thou wilt Live or Die Eternally. Do not delay the Lord, weary not his patience;<note place="margin">Jude 4.</note> turn not this Grace of God into laſciviouſneſs; <hi>Deſpiſe not the riches of his goodneſs, forbearance, and long-ſuffering, not knowing that the goodneſs of God leadeth thee to Repentance.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 2.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Take heed now, leſt there be in thee an evil heart of unbelief, in departing from the living God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 3.7, 8, 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Hear his voice, while it is called to day, leſt you be further hardned through the deceitfulneſs of ſin. Now is the day of thy viſitation, take care to know it, and improve it. This day is Salvation come to thine houſe;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lu. 19.41, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> verſe 9. Iſa. 65.2. Ezek. 18.32.</note> 
                  <hi>open thy heart and entertain it. Lay hold on Eternal Life, whilſt the Lords hand is ſtretched out all the day to offer it. Do not continue to walk in thy evil way, after thine own thoughts; but turn to the Lord, that thou maiſt live.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But perhaps thou wilt ſay, How gladly would I make this choice? but alas, I am ſo oppreſt with violence of Temptations, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106528:13"/>overpowered by my own vigorous corruptions; that my deſires are nipt in the bud, and prove abortive: ſo that I ſtill come ſhort and fail of the attainment. Beſides, I have no power in my ſelf, ſo much as to will, without Gods ſpecial Grace. And it is not of him that willeth,<note place="margin">Rom. 9.16.</note> nor of him that runneth, but of God that ſheweth mercy. But this is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in the ſecret of his own hidden counſel, unknown to me. For he hath <hi>mercy on whom he will have mercy, and whom he will he hardeneth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 18. Eccleſ 9 1.</note> And who knoweth either love or hatred, by all that is before him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> Yet are we not upon any of theſe conſiderations, to be diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged from this choice.<note place="margin">Vid. Chem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Exam. <hi>part 1.</hi> de fid. juſtific. Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h. Tom. <hi>3.</hi> de juſtific. <hi>c. 4. ſect. 96.</hi>
                  </note> As for that ſaying in <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.1. it is not right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly applied to this caſe, (though ſo much urged by the Papiſts, againſt the certitude of Divine Grace) as our Divines have abundantly proved. And let us further conſider, that God hath ſufficiently declared in his holy Word, how ſeriouſly he willeth, that we ſhould chooſe and enjoy this great bleſſing.<note place="margin">Deut. 29.29.</note> Why do we object againſt our ſelves his ſecret counſel (which belongeth not to us) and neglect his revealed Will, wherein he doth aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure us by his Oath, that he hath <hi>no pleaſure in the death of the wicked;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 33.11.</note> 
                  <hi>but rather that he ſhould turn from his way and live?</hi> And though the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of this Salvation (which is the end of our Faith, and holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation) be beyond the reach of any creatures merit;<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.9. Epheſ. 1.14. Iſa. 55.1. 2 Cor. 5.20. Ezek 18.31. John 5.40. 6.37.</note> yet it is pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed to our hand, by the precious blood of our Redeemer. And doth not the Lord freely offer it? Doth he not wooe us to it, and beſeech us to accept of it? Dot he not expoſtulate with thoſe that refuſe it; why they will die, and not come to him that they might have Life: And gives all aſſurance, that thoſe who come unto him, <hi>he will in no wiſe caſt out.</hi> If we deſpond in the ſenſe and apprehenſion of our own imbecillity,<note place="margin">2 Cor 3.5.</note> as not ſufficient of our ſelves, to think any thing as of our ſelves: Let us with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all conſider, that all our ſufficiency is of God, whoſe Grace is ſufficient for us, and who will perfect his ſtrength in weakneſs.<note place="margin">12.9.</note> He will work all our works in us: without whom indeed we can do nothing, but may do all things by him ſtrengthening us.<note place="margin">Iſa. 26.12. J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hn 15.5. Phil. 4.13. Rev. 22.12. Heb. 10.37. 2 Cor. 6 2. Iſa 45.9. Pſalm 145.19.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And that thou maiſt not think him long; he hath told thee, that he will come quickly, and not tarry: yea, that now is the accepted time; now is the day of ſalvation: Now, that he hath put it into thy heart to deſire it, to pant after it, to ſeek it, and pray for it. For he never ſaid to the ſeed of <hi>Jacob,</hi> that they ſhould ſeek his face in vain; but will fulfill the deſire of them that fear him, he will hear their cry, and will ſave them.</p>
               <p>Now that we may manage this choice aright, we muſt proceed by ſuch degrees, as reaſon directs in every conſiderable act, wherein the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding muſt perceive, the Will begin, Prudence direct, and Conſtancy perfect the Action. So it is here.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Take ſufficient cognizance of the things commended to thy choice, that thou chooſe not blind fold. We never enjoy the true benefit and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of our choice, till we know the excellency and uſe of it. Nor is it
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106528:14"/>accounted of as Worſhip, when we Worſhip God ignorantly, as the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 11.23. Pſalm 82.5. John 12.35. Deut. 15.21. Mal. 1.8.</note> and <hi>Athenians</hi> did. <hi>He that knoweth not, walketh on in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and knoweth not whither he goeth.</hi> And God will not accept a blind ſacrifice; it is an abomination to him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Will alſo muſt readily cloſe with this diſcovery: For an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing choice, is no choice. A wicked man may chooſe to act in ſome things vertuouſly, for fear of the puniſhment, that attends the contrary practice.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 9.7. Col. 3.23. 2 Cor 8.12.</note> The Lord loves chearful obedience, when we grudge not our Duty, nor do it as of neceſſity, but willingly. It pleaſeth him beſt, when the heart accompanies the work. A little with good will is accepted.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Conſult, and deliberate ſeriouſly, by what means thou maiſt accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh thy deſire and obtain this choice. In vain is a choice pretended, when the means is not attended. We can never hope, nor think to obtain this <hi>good part,</hi> but only in that way, and in the uſe of that means which God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed. In this caſe he hath ſo ordered, that the Means ſhould partake of the nature of the End. Salvation is begun in Holineſs, which is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Happineſs, and the Earneſt, and Firſt-fruits, and a Fore-taſt of Heavens joy.<note place="margin">Rom. 2 7, 10.</note> Glory, Honour, Immortality, and Eternal Life, and Peace ſhall be rendred unto them, who ſeek for it, by patient continuance in well doing. It is not idling at home, or following thy carnal pleaſures, or looking after thy worldly occaſions, when thou ſhouldſt be at Church in the ſolemn Worſhip of God, or in holy exerciſes in they Family, or in thy Cloſet, which will bring thee into acquaintance with the Almighty. For <hi>the friendſhip of the world is enmity with God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">James 4.4. 1 John 2.15.</note> And, <hi>if any man love the world, the love of the Father is not in him.</hi> Therefore <hi>Mary</hi> having made this choice of the End, ſhe likewiſe chooſeth the Means whereby it is obtained.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Having thus deliberately pitched upon the way, let there be a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute determination to enter upon it. Lay obligations upon thy ſoul to purſue this choice with all ſerious diligence. Thus <hi>David</hi> having conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered that bleſſedneſs belongs only to thoſe that <hi>are undefiled in the way,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 119.1, 2.</note> 
                  <hi>who walk in the Law of the Lord, and that keep his Teſtimonies, and ſeek him with their whole heart,</hi> and that it is Gods command, that we ſhould do ſo:<note place="margin">Verſe 5.</note> he ſtraightway falls to Prayer, that his waies might be ſo directed; and in the reſt of that devout <hi>Pſalm,</hi> he very frequently profeſſeth his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to walk in this way with all diligence: Yea, he binds himſelf by ſolemn vow to do it; <hi>I have ſworn</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and I will perform it, that I will keep thy righteous Judgements.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſe 106.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Yet all this is not ſufficient, unleſs we actually engage in the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and conſcientious uſe of the Means, whereby we may obtain our choice; of which we have ſpoken before; Trial 2.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Laſtly, It is neceſſary, that we perſevere unto the End; that we be not weary of well doing:<note place="margin">Gal. 6.9.</note> 
                  <hi>For in due ſeaſon we ſhall reap, if we faint not.</hi> The Promiſe (in the Epiſtles writ by Chriſts appointment) is <hi>Vincenti dabitur:</hi> The reward is given to him that overcometh. It is not ſaid
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106528:14"/>
                  <hi>Currenti</hi> or <hi>Pugnanti,</hi> to him that runneth, or to him that ſtriveth (though without theſe, no conqueſt) but to him that overcometh: As before, Trial 4.</p>
               <p>Thus much concerning <hi>Mary's</hi> Act: <hi>She hath choſen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. We are now to ſpeak of the Object, or <hi>thing choſen,</hi> viz. that <hi>good part which ſhall not be taken away from her.</hi> In which words the Object is deſcribed by two Prophecies: 1. It is <hi>good.</hi> 2. Durable, ſuch as <hi>ſhall not be taken away from her.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. It is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<hi>That good part.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The vulgar <hi>Latin</hi> Tranſlation calls it <hi>Optimam partem,</hi> that beſt part, as it is indeed, though the Original expreſs it only in the poſitive degree, which yet doth import the ſuperlative, calling it <hi>That good part</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> by way of excellency.</p>
               <p>We have before ſhewed how comprehenſive this <hi>one neceſſary thing is,</hi> having reſpect both to the End, and Means whereby the End is attained. And in that means we did more eſpecially conſider <hi>Mary</hi>'s preſent employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; which was to ſit at Jeſus Feet, and hear his Word.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Hom. Iliad <hi>1.</hi> de Neſtore.</note> Her Eyes and Ears did even hang upon his Lips, which were to her like <hi>Lillies dropping ſweet ſmelling Myrrhe,</hi> (Cant. 5.13.) <hi>How ſweet were his words unto her taſt? yea ſweeter than Honey to her mouth</hi> (Pſal. 119.103.) <hi>She ſate down under his ſhadow with great delight, and his fruit was ſweet to her taſt,</hi> Cant. 2.3.</p>
               <p>It is true: Hearing is but the Means to attain ſome degrees of this <hi>good part.</hi> But it being ſo conſiderable a part of <hi>Mary's Choice,</hi> and her preſent employment, and an evidence of her choice of the reſt; we ſhall conſider, how good it is.</p>
               <p>One obſerves (out of <hi>Seneca,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">To. de Trugill in feſt. Aſſumpt.</note> as he tells us) that all external things are <hi>propter corpus,</hi> for the Body, as Meat, Cloaths, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And that the Body is <hi>propter ſenſus,</hi> for the Senſes; that by corporal Organs we might perceive the wonderful works of God: and that the Senſes are <hi>propter mentem,</hi> for the Mind, being ſubſervient to it: and the Mind (in which are the rational faculties of underſtanding and will) is <hi>propter Deum;</hi> that we may attain to heavenly knowledge, and divine wiſdom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This alone were ſufficient to commend Hearing the Word of God, which tends to the perfecting of mans beſt part, and the obtaining of his ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt End. But to ſpeak ſomething more largely of it; Conſider that,</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is the Means which God hath ordained,<note place="margin">Acts 26.18. Rom. 12.2. John 5.25. Epheſ. 2.1. Nemo adeò ferus eſt, ut non mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſcere poſſit, Si modo culturae pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entem accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modet aurem, <hi>Hor. Ep.</hi> 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> to <hi>turn men from darkneſs to light, and from the power of Satan unto God.</hi> It changeth men from Sinners to Saints, from children of Wrath, to children of God, and Heirs of Heaven: transforming them thus by the renewing of their mind, whereby they come to prove what is that good, and acceptable, and perfect Will of God. It raiſeth from Death to Life: ſo were the <hi>Epheſians</hi> quickned, who before were dead in treſpaſſes and ſins. It will meeken and tame the fierceſt nature (as one ſaid well of Learning) forcing the moſt Tyger-like, and Lion like hearts (as they feigned of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106528:15"/>
                  <hi>Orpheus</hi>'s Harp) to lay aſide their bruitiſh, and cruel nature, and become tractable. It is by the power of the Goſpel thus received, <hi>That the Wolf ſhall dwell with the Lamb, and the Leopard ſhall lie down with the Kid,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and a little Child ſhall lead them.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 11.6, &amp;c.</note>
               </p>
               <p>This is the Fire and Hammer, wherewith God breaks the Rocks (the ſtonieſt hearts) in pieces. It makes the flintyeſt heart contrite and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and to tremble at the Hearing of it: whereby it becomes tractable, and ductile,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om. 6.37. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> apt to receive divine impreſſions. Hence the Apoſtle praiſeth God, who had ſo moulded the <hi>Romans,</hi> that they were delivered into that form or type of Doctrine (for ſo it is in the Greek) they were caſt into that mould, or received that ſtamp. Surely that which hath ſuch an happy operation upon the heart, muſt needs be good.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It leads the way to every other Duty. We hear, that we may learn; and learn that we may practiſe, and do that which we have learned. It is from hence that we are furniſhed with meet ſubjects for meditation, and with direction in our Prayers to God. By this we are inſtructed in our duty both to God and man. For it is this Grace of God which bringeth ſalvation,<note place="margin">Tit. 2.11, 12.</note> that teacheth <hi>us to deny ungodlineſs, and worldly luſts, and to live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this preſent world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. It is therefore preferred before other duties and employments. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha</hi>'s diligence in her careful and loving entertainment of Chriſt, is here ſet behind <hi>Mary</hi>'s devotion in hearing his Word. To offer ſacrifice was a neceſſary duty under the Law.<note place="margin">Exod. 23.15.</note> None muſt appear before the Lord emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Yet when this is neglected, ſacrifice is not eſteemed, but rather ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred. For <hi>to obey is better than ſacrifice: and to hearken, than the fat of Rams.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.22. Prov. 15.8. Jer. 6.19, 20. Iſa. 1.11.66.3.4. Pſalm 51.17. Iſa 66 2. Eccleſ. 5.1. Prov. 28.9. Acts 6 2. 1 Cor. 1.17. Praedicandi munus eſt pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, potius, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficilius &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. <hi>Par. in</hi> 1 Cor. 1.17.</note> 
                  <hi>But the ſacrifice of the wicked is an abomination to the Lord.</hi> When men do not hearken to his Word, but reject it: to what purpoſe is their bringing Incenſe from <hi>Sheba,</hi> &amp;c. Their burnt-offerings are not acceptable, nor their ſacrifices ſweet. The moſt acceptable ſacrifice is a broken ſpirit, and an heart that trembles at Gods Word. What ever men pretend in religious ſervice; if they be not ready to hear; all they do is in Gods account no better than the ſacrifice of Fools. And <hi>he that turneth away his ear from hearing the Law, even his Prayer ſhall he abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi> Therefore the Apoſtle preferred the Preaching of the Word be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Alms, and adminiſtring the Sacraments; which yet are neceſſery du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: but this is more excellent, difficult, and neceſſary; as being ordained for the ſalvation of all thoſe, that by true and lively Faith receive it; (<hi>Sam.</hi> 1.21. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16.) and without which, we know not how to perform the other.</p>
               <p>Now Hearing is the neareſt End of Preaching: therefore the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency that is aſcribed to Preaching, is for the ſake of Hearing.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It is the moſt excellent Antitode againſt the poiſon, and the malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of ſin. <hi>Now are ye clean</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>through the Word which I have ſpoken to you.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 15.3.17.17. Pſalm 119.9.</note> Even young men in that wanton and unruly Age may cleanſe their way by this means. For it diſcovers the uglineſs
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106528:15"/>of Sin; ſo that a mind well inſtructed, cannot but loath that abominable thing (which the Lord hates) and himſelf alſo,<note place="margin">Jer. 44.4. Ezek 6.9. Jam. 1.23. Eph. 5.12, 13.</note> for the evils that he hath committed in all his abominations. The Law of God is a mirrour or Glaſs, whereby a man may diſcover his ſpiritual deformities; <hi>it is the light which makes manifeſt the hidden things of darkneſs, and ſets them out in their proper colours;</hi> and that ſhews us the way wherein we ſhould walk, and guides our feet into the way of Peace.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It is indeed the Word of Eternal Life; the Word of Salvation;<note place="margin">John 6.68. Acts 13.26.20.32.</note> the Word of Gods Grace, which is able to build us up, and to give us an inheritance amongſt the ſanctified. Therefore to make choice of this, muſt needs be with <hi>Mary</hi> to chooſe <hi>that good part,</hi> whereof indeed this is the leaſt part, as but leading to that which doth compleat it.</p>
               <p n="2">II. The ſecond illuſtration of this Choice is, that this <hi>good part</hi> is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo durable, <hi>It ſhall not be taken away.</hi> This makes good the former: it is therefore the better good, becauſe permanent.<note place="margin">Pſalm. 1.3.</note> The fruit of this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Hearing ſhall never fade. <hi>Thoſe that are thus planted in the houſe of the Lord, ſhall flouriſh in the Courts of our God;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 92.13, 14. Boni operis tranſituri merces eſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies perman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſura. <hi>A g.</hi> Mat. 6.19, 20.</note> 
                  <hi>they ſhall bring forth fruit in old Age, they ſhall be fat and flouriſhing.</hi> The wages of this tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſient work ſhall be everlaſting reſt. <hi>This part ſhall not be taken away:</hi> For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. No enemy can take it away: no Thief can rob us of this treaſure. If any could, it muſt be either the Devil, or the World, or the Fleſh, or Death. But</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Devil cannot, notwithſtanding all his malice, power, or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty. The Gates of Hell, with all their temptations, terrours, or ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems can never deprive us of this choice. That enemy may tempt, and ſift, and buffet,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.5. Luk. 22.31, 32. 2 Cor. 12.7, 9.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But the grace of God is ſufficient to preſerve and uphold the ſoul in temptation; and through Chriſts interceſſion Faith ſhall not fail. He may thruſt ſore at the child of God, to make him fall; but the Lord will help.</p>
               <p>Upon reſiſtance he is forced to flee;<note place="margin">Pſalm 118.13. Jam. 4.7. Rom. 16.20. Gal. 2.20. Epheſ 3.17. Luke 11.22. 1 John 4.4.</note> and ſhall at length be trod under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot, through the power of Chriſt, who lives and dwells in every true Believer. The victory muſt certainly (in this caſe) fall to the ſtronger: and ſurely greater is he that is in his Saints, than he that is in the World.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The World cannot take it away, notwithſtanding all its enmity, and malignity, or its ſcorns, and reproaches, and cruel mockings, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions; or yet its ſnares, enticements,<note place="margin">John 16.33. 1 John 5.4, 5.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> There is power enough in Chriſt by Faith in him, to overcome it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Nor yet ſhall the Feſh, that remains in corrupt nature, ever be able to take it away; notwithſtanding all its averſeneſs to that which is good, or perverſeneſs, and ſtrong inclination to that which is evil.<note place="margin">Rom. 7.</note> Though it be rebellious, and luſt againſt the Spirit, and hindreth from duty, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voketh to ſin; yet ſhall it never prevail ſo far, as to deprive a Believer of his choice. For it is daily crucified, mortified,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.24.</note> and ſubdued by the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of divine Grace, which worketh mightily in every child of God. Though he be compaſſed about with this body of death, and forced to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106528:16"/>cry out with St. <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 7.23, 24.</note> 
                  <hi>O wretched man that I am,</hi> &amp;c. Yet he can alſo him thank God, that Jeſus Chriſt is his deliverer.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Neither yet can Death or any of its attendants take it away. For it is never able to ſeparate from the love of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Ro 8.35, &amp;c. 1 Cor. 15.54.</note> being ſwallowed up in that victory, which God giveth us through Chriſt our Lord.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As no enemy can, ſo God will not take it away. For 1. He delights in it,<note place="margin">Iſa. 57.15.</note> to ſee his children to make this choice. <hi>He whoſe Name is holy, who inhabiteth Eternity; whoſe Throne is the Heaven, and the Earth his foot-ſtool,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">66.1, 2.</note> &amp;c. Yet this Almighty God hath a ſpecial eye, to him that is of a poor and contrite ſpirit, and trembleth at his Word. For he ſees his own Image, and likeneſs there; wherewith he is ſo taken, that he is held in the Galleries to behold it.<note place="margin">Cant. 7.5. Pſalm 34.18. 1 Cor. 6.19. Pſa. 132.13, 14.</note> So great pleaſure doth he take in this, that he is ever nigh unto ſuch an heart, and delights to dwell in it. It is his Temple, his choſen and deſired habitation, his Reſt, where he will dwell, for he hath deſired it, and will take up his reſidence, and make his abode there. He engageth his Word and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe never to forſake it.<note place="margin">John 14.23. Heb. 13.5.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Beſides, it is the work of his own Spirit, by which he leads into all truth, brings the ſoul in frame, ſacrifices the whole man, kindles holy deſires, and fervent affections towards himſelf, and what ever may conduce to everlaſting happineſs. It is the Spirit which worketh all our works in us;<note place="margin">Iſa. 26.12. Rom. 8.26. Phil. 2.13.1.6.</note> helps our infirmities; gives both to will, and to do: and what he hath begun, he will not take off his hand, until he hath alſo finiſhed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Furthermore; it is part of the purchaſe of the blood of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſanctifie here, as well as to glorifie in Heaven. He hath procured both the Choice, and Grace to chooſe. And he ſhall ſurely obtain the fruit of his ſufferings: <hi>he ſhall ſee of the travel of his Soul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 53.11.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſhall be ſatisfied.</hi> Having paid an infinite ranſome for his Captives, he will take care, that they may be actual partakers of that dear bought Freedom. He will loſe none of thoſe, whom the Father hath given him:<note place="margin">John 6.39.17.12.</note> therefore he improves the opportunity of his exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the right hand of the Father, in making interceſſion for them; and a part of his Prayers in their behalf is,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.34. Luke 22.32. Joh. 17.11, 15, 17, 19, 23, 24.</note> that their Faith may not fail: but that they may be kept through the Name of the Father, from the evil that is in the World; and that they may be ſanctified through the Truth, which is his Word; that they may be made perfect in one; until they be with him, where he is, that they may behold his Glory.<note place="margin">Heb. 7.25. John 11.42. Heb. 5.7. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Vid. Par. Gerh. Eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> and à <hi>Lap.</hi> in loc.</note> Now he ever liveth to intercede thus for them, and he is ſure to ſpeed: for the Father will deny him nothing, and he is heard al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies for his Piety, or (as others) for his Dignity. All which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſidered, it muſt follow, that as he hath merited for them Grace to chooſe this <hi>good part,</hi> ſo likewiſe that what they have ſo choſen, ſhall never be taken away from them.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:106528:16"/>
               <p n="4">4. Yea, God hath laid upon himſelf a Covenant-engagement, to maintain this Priviledge, which he hath vouchſafed to his Saints. <hi>As for me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 59.21.</note> 
                  <hi>this is my Covenant with them</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>My Spirit which is upon thee, and my Words which I have put in thy mouth, ſhall not depart out of thy mouth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>from benceforth, and for ever.</hi> Again, <hi>I will put my fear in their hearts, and write it in their inward part, and I will be their God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer: 31.33.32.4. Heb. 13.5.</note> 
                  <hi>and they ſhall be my People: and I will put my fear in their hearts, that they ſhall not depart from me.</hi> Likewiſe he hath ſaid, <hi>I will never leave thee, nor forſake thee.</hi> And very aptly to our purpoſe, ſpeaks that Promiſe of our Saviour: <hi>Whoſoever drinketh of the water,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 4.14.</note> 
                  <hi>that I ſhall give him, ſhall never thirſt; but the water that I ſhall give him, ſhall be in him a Well of Water, ſpringing up into everlaſting Life.</hi> And in another place; <hi>He that believeth in me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 7.38. Tit. 1.2. 2 Tim. 2.13. Pſalm 119.49.</note> 
                  <hi>out of his Belly ſhall flow Rivers of living Water.</hi> Thus he hath promiſed, who is the God of Truth, and cannot Lie; and will not he remember the Word unto his Servants, wherein he hath cauſed them to hope? Surely he will ever be mindful of his Covenant; of the performance where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he hath given ſo many ſecurities:<note place="margin">105.8.111.5.</note> for he hath bound it with his Oath, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.17. and Seal, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.13. and Earneſt, <hi>ibid.</hi> verſ. 14. and the firſt fruits of his Spirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23. which is a bleſſed fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſt of Eternal Happineſs, in ſome degrees of that joy of the Holy Ghoſt, which is unſpeakable and full of Glory, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8. and of that <hi>Peace of God which paſſeth all underſtanding,</hi> Phil. 4.7. And ſhall we think all this to be in vain? as indeed it might be, if it could be taken away. No ſurely; his deſign in theſe various confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of his Promiſe, and of our Faith in it is, that by ſuch immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table things, wherein it is impoſſible for God to Lie,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.18.</note> we might have ſtrong conſolation.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> This <hi>good part</hi> ſo choſen and enjoyed is of a ſpiritual and divine nature.<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.4.</note> Although through the ſtrength of remaining corruption, and the violence of temptation it may for the time be obſcured, and eclipſed: yet it ſhall never be extinguiſhed, and utterly loſt.</p>
               <p>This Reed may be ſhaken, and bruiſed;<note place="margin">Mat. 12 20.</note> but ſhall not be quite broken: This Flax may be reduced to ſmoaking, but ſhall not utterly be quenched.</p>
               <p>The Seed that is ſown ſhall remain,<note place="margin">1 John 3.9.</note> though for a time it lie hid under-ground, yet the Prolifick vertue that is in it will make a ſeaſonable appearance, that it was not dead when it lay hid.<note place="margin">Job 19.28.</note> The root of the matter is ſtill in him, who is once planted in the Courts of the Houſe of our God; ſo that he ſhall ſtill bring forth,<note place="margin">Pſalm 92.13.</note> though ſometimes (for the while) his branches ſhew neither Fruit nor Leaves; yet that Sap which is retired to the heart and root, will certainly put forth its vigour again, and produce both Leaves and Fruit. The things
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106528:17"/>that are choſen,<note place="margin">Col. 3.1. 2 Cor. 4.18. Col. 1.5. 2 Tim. 4.8. Mat. 25.34. 1 Pet. 1.4, 5.</note> are above; things not ſeen, and eternal; our Hope and Crown is laid up for us in Heaven; the Kingdom and Inheritance was prepared for us from the Foundation of the World; and it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oorruptible, and fadeth not away, being reſerved in Heaven for us; and we our ſelves are kept by the power of God through Faith unto Salvation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How ſhould theſe things be; if this <hi>good part</hi> ſo choſen could be taken away?</p>
               <p>Since therefore this <hi>one thing</hi> is ſo neceſſary, ſo good, uſeful and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable; and withal ſo durable, that when we are once actually poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of it, we can never be wholly deprived of it: What remains; but that we prefer it in our eſteem, according to its worth, before all things in the World: and ſpeedily reſolve (as we were before exhorted) to make this Choice with <hi>Mary?</hi> To which the Lord direct us, and in it aſſiſt us, for his great Names ſake: To whom with our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the Holy Ghoſt, that ever bleſſed Unity in Trinity, and Trinity in Unity, be all Glory, Honour, and Praiſe now and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:106528:17"/>
            <head>A <hi>Narrative</hi> of the Religious and Holy Life and Death, of the Lady <hi>Mary,</hi> late Wife of S<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Thomas Whar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> Knight of the <hi>Bath:</hi> In great part as it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered at her Funeral, with many material paſſages ſince added.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving now done with the Text, it will juſtly be expected, that I ſhould ſpeak ſomething of that Heavenly Soul, whoſe Corps are now to be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terred; to ſolemnize whoſe Funerals, ſo many Noble and Worthy Perſons are here congregated. She was a very ſutable Parallel to Her in the Text, both in her Name and Choice. Nor will it ſeem ſtrange to thoſe that knew her, that ſhe ſhould be in ſome degree matched with thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned <hi>Maries,</hi> whom we have had occaſion to mention (the Mother of our bleſſed Saviour only excepted, who was favoured, and bleſſed above all Women) had ſhe but enjoyed the Priviledge of their oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities, to have given like evidence of her great Devotion, and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly affection.</p>
            <p>Her Extraction was Noble and Honourable (as this <hi>Mary</hi>'s in the Text is probably ſuppoſed to be) being the Eldeſt Daughter of the late Right Honourable <hi>Henry</hi> Earl of <hi>Dover,</hi> whoſe Grandfather was the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned <hi>Henry</hi> Lord <hi>Hunſdon,</hi> Couſin German, by the Mothers ſide, to that moſt excellent Queen of ever bleſſed memory, Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> Her Mother was of the Antient and Worthy Family of the <hi>Pelhams,</hi> of <hi>Haland</hi> in <hi>Suſſex,</hi> called Lady <hi>Judick,</hi> Daughter of Sir <hi>Thomas Pelham,</hi> whoſe Anceſtors were of great Note many hundred years ago, meriting for Chivalry, in the ſervice of their King and Country, an acceſs of Honour, which is yet born in their Arms.</p>
            <p>She was Born <hi>November</hi> 13. 1615. being the third Child (after two
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106528:18"/>Sons) and the Eldeſt Daughter of her Parents: who had beſides her, three Sons (of whom, the Right Honourable <hi>John</hi> Earl of <hi>Dover</hi> is yet living) and three Daughters, all eminent for Piety, and all commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble endowments, whereof two are with the Lord, and one yet ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving. Her Mother died, leaving them very young: yet ſhe having the advantage of ſeven years more than the Eldeſt of her other Siſters, ſupplied a Mothers care of them, in their tender years. And what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence her inſtructions, advice, and gracious example in all her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment had upon them was very evident, in their early proficiency in all Vertue, and gracious imitation of ſo fair a Copy.</p>
            <p>It pleaſed God, who had made Choice of her for himſelf before all time,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.1. In ſeculo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis apud Deum cupit eſſe nobilior. <hi>Auth. Epiſt. ad Demetriadem.</hi> Ab illuſtribus naſci, Deo per ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum renaſci. Nobilis gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, ſed multo nobilior ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitate. <hi>Hier. E.</hi> 27. <hi>ad Euſtoch.</hi> de <hi>Paula.</hi> —Nobilitas ſola eſt, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> unica virtus, <hi>Juv. Sat.</hi> 8. Illa dives, quae in Deo eſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves. <hi>Cypr.</hi> de <hi>hab. Virg.</hi> Dan. 11.21. 1 Kin. 21.20, 25 Epheſ. 2.2. 2 Tim. 2.26. Rom. 6.12. 2 Pet. 2.19. Non eſt quod ſibi aliquis de nobilitate ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neris blandia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ſi ex meli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ore parte ſit famulus. Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tò eſt indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us mente ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vire quam cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore. <hi>Auth. Ep.</hi> ad <hi>Demetr.</hi>
               </note> to work her to a ſerious Choice of his waies in the beſt time: <hi>To remember her Creator in the daies of her youth.</hi> For even in thoſe frail times, which moſt others waſte, and ravel out in folly and vanity, ſhe received ſuch an happy tincture of true Piety, and the fear of God, as never loſt, but ever increaſed its luſtre till her laſt breath. This advanced her pious Soul above all carnal priviledges of Nobility, Anceſtry, and all terrene Glories derived from her eminent Progenitors, to fix upon that which was only able to make her truly Noble and Glorious. She was indeed Noble in the account of the World; but not ſatisfied with that, her deſire was to be more Noble in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>Her Heaven-born Faith trampled under-foot all conceit, or conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſecular advantage. It was no great matter to her, to iſſue from illuſtrious Progenitors: her greateſt ambition was to become the Child of God by ſpiritual birth. She eſteemed it but a ſmall thing to glitter with the Enſigns of a Noble Family, whoſe great care was to be enrol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led among the Saints, and Family of God. She forgot her ſelf to be Rich or Honourable; regarding it only ſo far, that the holineſs of her mind, might exceed the ſplendour of her outward man: For ſhe eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that to be the greateſt, which is the trueſt Nobility, <hi>viz.</hi> to be the Child of God, and co-heir with Chriſt. Being thus perſwaded, her conſtant endeavour was to preſerve the honour of her Nobility, by keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it unſtained from thoſe Vices, which are not only a blemiſh to it, but leave the offenders (how Nobly ſo ever extracted) under the ignominy of degeneracy, and in the rank of the vileſt of men; who ſell them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to work wickedneſs in the ſight of the Lord; whereby they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come willing ſlaves to the Prince of darkneſs, who worketh effectually in and by them, leading them Captive at his Will. Whilſt they ſerve their own Luſts, and ſuffer ſin to reign in their mortal bodies, obeying it in the luſts thereof; they even proclaim themſelves to be the ſervants of ſin, being by it vanquiſhed, and brought in bondage. She well knew, that no man hath any cauſe to boaſt of his Nobility, when his better part is enſlaved; it being much more ſhameful to enſlave the mind than the body. Her care therefore was to transfer all outward advantages, to the inward adorning of the Soul; ſlighting all ſecular Pomp and ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106528:18"/>that ſhe might with more freedom chooſe <hi>that good part,</hi> which could <hi>not be taken away from her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having ſo early received into her tender heart the Heavenly dew of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Grace; natural corruption (that common diſeaſe of all mankind) was thereby even nipt in the bud, and received its Deaths-wound before it could get that advantage, which it ordinarily obtaineth in miſerable mortals.</p>
            <p>How ſoon did ſhe begin to perform her Baptiſmal Vow and Covenant, renouncing the Devil and all his works, the pomps and vanities of this wicked World, and all the ſinful luſts of the Fleſh? Thoſe vanities which were the carnal delights and darlings of her equals, were her burden and grievance. When to pleaſe Relations, and that ſhe might not ſeem too ſcrupulouſly moroſe, ſhe was ſome-waies neceſſitated to be preſent at the interludes which were at certain times acted in the Family; yet (as I have heard her ſometimes ſay) her heart was otherwiſe employ'd, and ſhe would ever be ſure to take the firſt opportunity to withdraw, and retire her ſelf from thoſe vanities, to exerciſe her thoughts in better meditations, according to her (yet ſlender) capacity.</p>
            <p>Being grown up to years of diſcretion, when her towardlineſs was more conſpicuous in her Religious and Gracious comportment; how dear and precious was ſhe to all ſuch of her acquaintance, as had devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelves to the fear of God? She was ever beloved and honoured by them; and they of all others were moſt dear to her.</p>
            <p>Whilſt ſhe kept in her Fathers-Houſe, and afterwards till the day of her Marriage, beſides her ſecret retirements, ſhe was a diligent Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant upon publick Ordinances; not omitting to watch at Wiſdoms gates, and wait at the Poſts of her Houſe continually. Inſomuch as, living under the Miniſtry of that Eminent and faithful Servant of Chriſt, Doctor <hi>Holdeſworth,</hi> ſhe would not miſs either Lords-Daies, nor Holy-Daies Sermons, nor Mornings Prayers, on Wedneſdaies and Frydaies, nor ſuch times in the Week as he appointed for Catechiſe: though ſhe was conſtrained hereby to leave her mornings reſt very early; and for haſte cover with her Scarfe the defects of thoſe Dreſſes, which detained others of her Rank, from that, which ſhe more prized, than all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gayeties.</p>
            <p>But theſe were her more obſcure times before ſhe was ſo fully known to thoſe, who are yet living, witneſſes of her pious regard to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly practices. From whoſe credible reports, and my own knowledge in the (O too ſhort) time of our acquaintance (which was not full two years) take theſe enſuing few Obſervations.</p>
            <p>It was the thirtieth year of her Age, before ſhe gave way to any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Marriage (though ſhe had many from very conſiderable perſons) but at that time it pleaſed God, who ordereth all the concernments of his dear Children for their aſſured good, to preſent her with ſuch a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as could not but be acceptable to her, <hi>viz.</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Wharton,</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:106528:19"/>Knight of the <hi>Bath,</hi> and only Brother to the Kight Honourable <hi>Phillip</hi> Lord <hi>Wharton</hi> of <hi>Wharton:</hi> who being well acquainted with that Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily (to which his was nearly allied) took ſo much notice of her Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and gracious converſation (the great attractive of his affections to her) that gave him occaſion to move her in order to Marriage. Which motion (moſt happy to them both) ſhe upon ſerious conſideration did embrace; yet with this proviſion (ſuch due regard ſhe had to filial duty) that her Fathers, and her Uncle Sir <hi>Thomas Pelham</hi>'s conſent (whom ſhe ever honoured as a Father, and he ever tenderly loved her as a Child) ſhould firſt be obtained. Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> was at hand, and therefore the firſt addreſs was made to him, who readily and chearfully gave his approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Her Father was then at <hi>Oxford</hi> with the King, and his whole Eſtate under ſequeſtration; nor had ſhe any further expectation from him of any augmentation of that Portion, which was long before in her own hands, and diſpoſe; yet would ſhe not Marry, till his aſſured con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent was gained, to her full ſatisfaction; which himſelf did ſignifie to her by divers Letters (which I have ſeen) written from <hi>Oxford:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he declared, that he was aſſured, that Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> would prove both honeſt and kind; and farther aſſured her, that his bleſſing ſhould accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany them in their Marriage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now was the time, when that light of Divine Grace, long ſince kindled, muſt become more conſpicuous, ſhining more and more unto that perfect day.<note place="margin">Prov. 4.18.</note> Now that precious ſeed, which had taken ſuch firm root in her heart, and had already made a hopeful progreſs in the blade, ſhall produce the Ear, and after that the full Corn in the Ear, and yield the great Husband-man an acceptable Harveſt.<note place="margin">Mark 4.28.</note>
            </p>
            <p>To mention the particular paſſages of her well ſpent Life, would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be to write an Hiſtory, than (what is only intended) a ſhort Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative. I can therefore here give only a general account of ſome few paſſages, which yet may ſufficiently evidence the ſincerity of her Faith, working by Love, which is the whole of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>What is intended may be referred to theſe two Heads; 1. Her Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification. 2. Her Converſation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the former of theſe; She was a careful obſerver of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles earneſt Exhortation; adding to her <hi>Faith Vertue, and to Vertue, Knowledge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.5.</note> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The odious aſperſion of Solifidianiſm could not be faſtened on her; though in the point of Juſtification, ſhe depended only and wholly upon the righteouſneſs of Chriſt imputed to the Believer, and received by Faith: in this caſe not at all looking at her own inherent righteouſneſs. Her Faith was a lively and active Faith, manifeſting its vigour and genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine nature by its proper fruits. It provoked thoſe Vertues, wherewith ſhe was plentifully furniſhed,<note place="margin">Virtus, à vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus, quaſi vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri vis. <hi>Varro.</hi> de <hi>Ling. Lat.</hi> lib. 4.</note> to exert their force and ſtrength (whence they are ſo called.) in the production of every good work as ſhe had opportunity.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:106528:19"/>
            <p>And becauſe ſhe was perſwaded it was as neceſſary to do well, as to do good; which cannot be without ſome good competency of knowledge to direct each vertuous action: Therefore ſhe gave all diligence, to add to her Vertue Knowledge; not only ſpeculative, whereby ſhe knew what ſhe ought to do; but practical, in doing what ſhe knew: which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the advantage of a further degree, <hi>viz.</hi> experimental knowledge; by which means ſhe reaped the ſweeteſt comfort, which ariſeth from the conſcience of well-doing. Her knowledg was ſavoury, and her judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſound in the things that concern ſalvation. She was never tainted with Novel opinions, and fancies; but well acquainted with, and tena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious of the form of ſound words contained in the holy Scriptures; and as they are taught in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> whereof ſhe was a true and dutiful Child. So well was ſhe grounded in the Principles and main points of Religion, that ſhe was out of the reach of the ſubtileſt Papiſts ſeduction; as ſhe ſometimes was not free from their attempts, but ever from their Impreſſions.</p>
            <p>Moreover, knowing that whilſt we are in this Tabernacle, we bear in our boſoms a rebel to the law of our mind; the Fleſh luſting againſt the Spirit; that ſhe might ſubdue and mortifie that enemy, ſhe gave all diligence to add to her knowledge, temperance,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Maenand.</note> that promptuary of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, moſt remarkable.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In her eminent and exemplary Modeſty, and Chaſtity. She never came within the reach of the moſt curious ſuſpicion of Immodeſty, Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin or Wife: being ever careful to abſtain from all appearance of evil by any wanton word or geſture.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In her moderate uſe of thoſe <hi>ſubſidia,</hi> which our heavenly Father knows are needful for us, and therefore is pleaſed to allow us for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of our Life.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In her Apparel. She reſtrained her ſelf from the uſe of thoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions, which though in themſelves they are unſeemly (to ſay no worſe) yet are too frequent and common in uſe amongſt ſuch as were her equals:<note place="margin">Peccandi fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta, Lupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap> inſignia, ornamenta Meretricum, <hi>&amp;c. Cypr.</hi> de <hi>hab. Virg. Tertul.</hi> de <hi>hab. Mal.</hi> &amp; de cult. Foeminarum. Vide etiam, <hi>Aug. Epiſt.</hi> 73. &amp; de Doctr. Chriſt. l. 4. c. 21. <hi>Ambr.</hi> l. 1. de <hi>Virg. Hier. Epiſt.</hi> 10. 1 Pet. 3.3, 4.</note> whereby the practice is become incorrigible, and the contrary diſdained by the exorbitant. She never uſed to bare her Breaſts and Shoulders, or Paint, or Spot her Face, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or any ſuch Dreſs, as were ever exploded by all ſober Chriſtians, and vehemently reproved by the Primitive Fathers, as enticements, and provocations of Luſt, ornaments of light perſons, and inventions of the Devil, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But this chaſt Soul abhorred to be ſo disfigured. Her ornaments were not broidered or platted Hair, Gold, or Pearls, or coſtly array (though ſhe wanted none of thoſe things, if ſhe had fancied them) but the hidden man of the Heart. Her beſt Dreſs was that ſhamefac'dneſs and Sobriety commanded by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> (1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.9.) and the incorruptible (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) of a meek and quiet ſpirit, which St. <hi>Peter</hi> tells us, takes ſuch worth in the ſight of God. This is the Dreſs which <hi>Tertullian</hi> commends to Chriſtian Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106528:20"/>men:<note n="*" place="margin">Veſtite vos ſerico probita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, byſſino ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitatis, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purâ pudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae. Taliter pigmentatae Deum habebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Amatorem. <hi>Tert.</hi> de cultu foemin. in fine.</note> 
               <hi>Cloath your ſelves</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>with the Silk of Honeſty, with the Sattin of Sanctity, with the Purple of Modeſty: in ſuch Paints God will be your Lover.</hi> In ſuch attire would ſhe appear before God, as ſhe knew was beſt pleaſing to him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Nor was her Temperance leſs remarkable in reference to her Diet: being nothing ſtudious, or deſirous of dainty or coſtly Fare. Her or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary food was good and wholeſome; but plain, and ſuch as is moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate for the ends for which God hath ordained it: <hi>viz.</hi> preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Health, and increaſe of ſtrength: not to pleaſe a dainty Palate, or gratifie an exorbitant Appetite, and excite Luſt. But the ordering of Family proviſions by her appointment, was plentiful, as to ordinary Houſe-keeping; generous and free in her entertainments, to the great contentment of her Friends and equals: whoſe Viſits were exceeding frequent and grateful.</p>
            <p>Neither was ſhe wanting to add fortitude to her other Vertues; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely perſiſting in well-doing, being ſtrengthened with power by the Spirit in the inward man,<note place="margin">Eph. 3.16.</note> to reſiſt the temptation, and overcome the difficulties, which are ever ready to obſtruct all godly endeavours. She was indeed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Woman of valour, never weary of well-doing, nor faint in her mind:<note place="margin">Prov. 31.10. Lxx. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. v. L. Mulier fortis. Gal. 6.7. Heb. 12.3. Job 17.9. Heb. 10.23. Rev. 2.10.</note> but held on in her way, growing yet ſtronger and ſtronger, ſhe held faſt her Profeſſion, and was faithful unto the End, that ſhe might obtain the promiſed Crown.</p>
            <p>But the Crown of all her Vertues was her Sincerity. They were not in ſhew only, but in reality and truth: ſhe was what ſhe ſeemed; her Gold needed no Gilt. She was (as is ſaid of the Kings Daughter, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.13.) glorious within, as well as without. Her hidden man was richly furniſhed; though not ſo much expoſed to the eye of man, as of him who ſeeth in ſecret, and ſearcheth the heart and reins. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, though it be moſt difficult to determine of any mans ſincerity, which is only know to him, that is the diſcerner of the thoughts and intentions of the heart; yet where there are ſuch clear appearances, and ſatisfactory evidences; he muſt be leſs than a Chriſtian, that hath not ſo much Charity, as to conclude that ſuch a one as ſhe, muſt needs be ſincere: who did ſo uniformly practiſe godlineſs to the laſt period of her Life; never varying, or abating in her godly care and watchfulneſs, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies proceeding in a conſtant tenor of an holy converſation, according to that invariable rule, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16. Her univerſal cloſing with all good, and deteſtation of all ſin, abſtaining from the very appearance of evil; hating ſin both in her ſelf and others: her fervent zeal for Gods glory; her cordial Love, and vehement affection to, and conſtant uſe of all his holy Ordinances: her ready ſubmiſſion to his Will in all things; her fear to offend him in any thing; her grief frequently expreſſed, that ſhe was not more holy; her earneſt deſire of and longing for farther aſſurance of divine favour; her exemplary Humility, ever having low thoughts of her ſelf, and of any thing ſhe did, alwaies acknowledging her great
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:106528:20"/>defects in each Duty, and her unworthineſs of the leaſt mercy; eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her ſelf the greateſt of ſinners, and the leaſt of all Saints (as St. <hi>Paul</hi>) nothing eſteeming any thing ſhe was or did,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1. 15, Epheſ. 3.8. Phil. 3.8. Opibus &amp; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptâ, facta eſt in humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate nobilior, <hi>Hier. Ep.</hi> 16. Pſalm 50.23.</note> no not her greateſt attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in Grace and Holineſs (as to any dependence upon them) much leſs her outward priviledges of Nobility, and worldly greatneſs, that ſhe might gain Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">II. As for her Converſation it was ſutable to her Qualifications; ever ſtudying to walk according to the rule of holineſs. Her great care was to prepare her heart to ſeek the Lord: that ſhe might in all things order her converſation aright, both towards God and man.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In reſpect of God, what is ſaid in Scripture of <hi>Enoch, Noah,</hi> and other holy perſons, that they walked with God, was alſo verified in her.</p>
            <p>How ſhe did deport her ſelf in ſecret duties, was known only to God, and her own Soul: according to her Saviours admonition. Yet if we may meaſure her more retired Devotions,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.6.</note> by what was evident in Church and Family Duties, nothing could be more affectionate. Her ſecret Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, as alſo her Meditations, and heavenly raptures were more immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate exchanges between her pious Soul, and him whom her Soul loved. Some part whereof could not yet be ſo concealed, but that ſuch as were near her, could obſerve her conſtant retirements, and by her Diſcourſes take notice (at leaſt in general) how her time was employed in her Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet. For ſuch is the nature of true Love, that it cannot contain, but muſt at ſometimes break forth in the praiſes of its beloved, and expreſs its joys and heavenly content in him whom it ſo much admires; as is evident by the Diſcourſe of the Church in the <hi>Canticles.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Cant. 2.16 5.10, &amp;c. 6.3.7.10.</note> Thoſe raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing joys cannot be concealed: the Daughter of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the excellencies of her beloved, and how exceedingly ſhe is affected with, and to him.</p>
            <p>Thus much, and much more was known to her dear and indulgent Husband (who himſelf was not only an incourager, but alſo an excellent example and Pattern of private Devotions) as followeth:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Her diligent and careful Reading of the holy Scriptures, which being a conſiderable part of her retirements, brought her to a famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar acquaintance with the revealed Will of God. She tasked her ſelf with Reading a daily portion; which was ſtudiouſly performed. And what good uſe ſhe made thereof, may be gathered from her Obſervations which were found among her Papers written with her own hand,<note place="margin">Prov. 3.3. Theſe were called <hi>Tota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>photh,</hi> or <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacteries,</hi> and by the Rabbins <hi>Tephilin.</hi> Of which read. <hi>Buxtorf. Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gog. Jadaic.</hi> cap. 4. <hi>Ainſw.</hi> &amp; <hi>Synopſ. Critic.</hi> in Exod. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> which I have ſeen and peruſed: wherein no leſs than three hundred remarkable paſſages were tranſcribed <hi>verbatim,</hi> to be the ſubject of her private Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and that ſhe might more firmly imprint them in her memory, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that injunction of <hi>Solomon:</hi> write them upon the Table of thy heart. Thus the Lord commanded the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> that they ſhould write certain Sections of the Law, which they ſhould wear upon their hands, and as Frontlets before their eyes: that the Law might be had in perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al remembrance. Theſe were in time ſuperſtitiouſly, and hypocritically
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:106528:21"/>abuſed, as appears, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.5. But ſhe was far from oſtentation, nor was this pious care of hers known till after her death. Amongſt others, theſe Scriptures ſhe moſt eſpecially propoſed to her Reading and Meditation, at ſuch times as ſhe ſet apart for private humiliation, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61. <hi>Ezr.</hi> 9. <hi>Neh.</hi> 9. <hi>Joel</hi> 2. <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.9, 10. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.18. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Neh.</hi> 1. ad 10. I have tranſcribed them as they were found in her Papers.</p>
            <p>And as ſhe was thus diligent in reading the holy Scripture: ſo did ſhe alſo take great pains and delight in reading of ſuch Books as were written by thoſe worthy perſons, who were of greateſt eſteem among the moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and religious Readers. For as her great deſign in reading was to underſtand the good, and acceptable, and perfect Will of God; ſo ſhe rationally conceived,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.2.</note> that none could more likely acquaint her with the mind of God, than thoſe who were deſigned to this Office, and who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed moſt with him in their pious, exemplary, and conſtant practice: remembring that the ſecret of the Lord is with them that fear him, and he will ſhew them his Covenant.<note place="margin">Pſalm 25.14. Prov. 3.32. Theſe Authors were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to her by B. <hi>uſher,</hi> and others who were ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> Amongſt theſe, ſhe chiefly read Mr. <hi>Daniel Dyke,</hi> of the deceitfulneſs of the Heart (a Book ſhe highly prized, and oft times read over) Mr. <hi>Arth. Hilderſham</hi>'s works alſo, and Dr. <hi>Preſton</hi>'s, Dr. <hi>Sibs,</hi> Mr. <hi>Dod,</hi> Mr. <hi>Rogers</hi>'s ſeven Treatiſes, and the Epitome, called The Practice of Chriſtianity; Mr. <hi>John Downham</hi>'s Chriſtian Warfare, though very voluminous, yet could not the bigneſs of any good Book prevent, but rather excite her diligence.</p>
            <p>Near her end ſhe was Reading Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Inſtitutions (tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh</hi>) the ſecond time, having not many weeks before Read it quite through.</p>
            <p>Many other ſuch good and practical Authours ſhe had carefully Read with great profit, turning their words into Works. For ſhe was ever care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, not only to take in more light by ſuch good mens pains, but chiefly to feel her heart warmed by their kindly heats. She uſed her Reading in ſtead of a Looking-Glaſs, whereby to diſcover and reform, whatſoever was amiſs in her practice; and alſo how to adorn her converſation with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular obedience: ſo that her Reading did not only enrich her mind with knowledge, but beautifie her life with vertuous practice; knowing that God hath given us his Word and Law, not only to be known, but to be actually obeyed. For what doth it profit, to learn what we ſhould do, if we do not what we have learned? When ſhe would recreate her mind with any pleaſant Diſcourſe; beſides her Reading of ſerious Hiſtory, ſhe took great delight in Reading Mr. <hi>Herbert</hi>'s Verſes, moſt of which ſhe could repeat without Book. Theſe her recreation inſtead of Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>books, and Romances.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Beſides her diligent and unwearied Reading (which was not only part of her Cloſet work, but uſually her afternoons employment, when not hindred by company, or not exerciſed in needle-work, for ſhe was never idle) ſhe conſtantly obſerved her deſigned and ſlated times for ſecret Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. In which if ſhe were at any time hindred by entertainment of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:106528:21"/>friends, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet would ſhe redeem time even from her ſleep, rather than ſhorten her accuſtomed Devotions.</p>
            <p>And here though no other account can be expected, than of every pious Soul,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.6. 2 Sam. 7.18. Dam. 6.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> whoſe care is not to be ſeen or heard in thoſe retirements by any but their heavenly Father: yet by providence ſomething was found among her Papers, written with her own hand upon a ſpecial occaſion, which may afford ſome diſcovery of her godly and devout frame of Spirit, even in that heavenly and ſecret Duty.</p>
            <p>The occaſion was this: That Reverend and holy man of God Mr. <hi>John Hudſon</hi> (now the Right Reverend Biſhop of <hi>Elphin</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi>) Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon that Text, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.27. <hi>For this Child I prayed,</hi> &amp;c. amongſt other ſavoury paſſages obſerved; That Mercies and Bleſſings obtained by Prayer will be ſweet, and that we ſhould eſpecially record ſpecial mercies, which practice would both help our memory (we being very apt to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get mercies, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.7.) and alſo ſtrengthen our Faith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 85.1, 2, 3, &amp;c. verſ. 8, 9. <hi>I will hear what God the Lord will ſpeak,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Surely his Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is nigh them that fear him.</hi> Her gracious Soul made ſuch good uſe of that Sermon, that ſhe from that time reſolved to keep a Record of ſuch ſpecial mercies, as it ſhould pleaſe the Lord to vouchſafe her; more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſuch, as were given in upon Prayer. And in thoſe Papers wherein they were found Recorded, ſhe thus beſpeaks the Lord in her Prayers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O my God, I deſire now to come before thee, humbled in my Soul for my own baſeneſs and filthineſs from Head to Foot: Every member of my Body being ready and inclined to every ſin; every faculty of my Soul being polluted and defiled with that foul and ugly ſin, wherein I was conceived and born. And to aggravate this; having received, and ſtill poſſeſſing more mercies, and gracious diſpenſations from thee, than (I think) ever any creature had. But it is thy free-grace, who canſt as well give me a thankful heart, as a receiving hand: which I beg for his ſake, upon whoſe account only I come before thee, and have this confidence to approach unto thee. And here, O Lord, through thine aſſiſtance I deſire to recount, as I am able, ſome of thoſe innumerable mercies, that I daily receive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then after an enumeration of many general mercies, ſhe thus proceeds. <hi>Good God, give me the Grace likewiſe, that all this thy goodneſs may not be in vain upon my poor Soul.— I bleſs thy Name for the gracious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of thy bleſſed Spirit, at all times, when I ſet my ſelf before thee in earneſt to ſeek thy face and favour in private; and in eſpecial at a Faſt I kept, and Sacrament I received, when I was left all alone at</hi> Wobourn, <hi>when I received much comfort,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Then again reckoning up many particular mercies received at the Lords hand upon her Prayers to him, for her Husband and Son: amongſt which ſhe forgets not affectionatly to mention the good means of Grace and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, they had lived under, and the contented, peaceable, plentiful, chearful condition they had enjoyed ever ſince they came together. <hi>But theſe</hi> (ſaith ſhe) <hi>are but Ones of thouſands, that I have and do enjoy. O give
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:106528:22"/>me to live in ſome meaſure anſwerable to this goodneſs of thine,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>After this manner hath ſhe Recorded the many ſpecial mercies, deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, bleſſings, which ſhe, her Husband, Son, and Family had received; note<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the day and month of the year. And the whole contexture is in the ſame tenour of Prayer and Praiſes; ever deſiring of the Lord, that he would give her to live the life of Faith, and Thankſgiving, which was her fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent expreſſion. But the particular mercies conferred upon her ſelf and her Relations, were not the only Subject of her thankful praiſes. So great was her affection to the Church of God, and to her dear native Country, that publick bleſſings were alſo ſound Recorded in her ſecret Devotions. Thus when it pleaſed God to heal the breaches of this diſtracted Nation, by the happy Reſtauration of his Royal Majeſty: ſhe thus expreſſeth her deep ſenſe of that wonderful change. <hi>But now, O God, I am confounded, and know not what to ſay, nor which way to begin to bleſs and praiſe by great Name for thy infinite preſervations of, deliverances to, and bleſſed reſtauration of our dear King, and his Family from their ſad baniſhed, and diſtracted condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which they have long lain under, to their own Inheritance. And all this is beyond what we could have asked or thought; to be without blood, or obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to ſtrangers, or any thing but thy own hand, which is for ever to be mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified, and adored for this great Work; for which I beſeech thee to give me, and all thine, to live the life of Faith and Thankſgiving; to lay our ſelves in the duſt, and to be low in our own eyes, that thou alone maiſt be exalted for theſe great and wonderful things, that thou haſt done in our daies, for preſerving them in the true Religion in the midſt of diverſe temptations, and keeping them from diverſe dangers of Soul and Body: for all which let our Souls bleſs thy great Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This may ſuffice to give ſome aim, whereby to meaſure her private Devotions, which could not otherwiſe be diſcovered, but by her own Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, occaſioned as is before declared. But by this it may appear, how ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſhe was in her Meditation of Gods loving-kindneſs to her, and her Relations in every concernment: with which ſhe was ſo exceedingly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, that ſhe could not forbear to ſpeak of it in her private diſcourſes with her friends. In the ſhort time of our acquaintance, how frequently have I heard her, with tears of joy expreſs her deep apprehenſions of Gods gracious Providence in their outward proſperity beyond her hopes; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miring his bleſſings, according to his holy promiſe, heaped upon them, ſhe knew not how; owing his hand, and diſowning all their own care and endeavour, as of no ſignification in reference to the greatneſs of (even outward) mercies received.</p>
            <p>This wrought her Soul to the higheſt content with that Eſtate which it pleaſed God to place her in: which had it been much meaner, would yet no doubt, have been acceptable to her thankful heart, which ever took its meaſure from the conſideration of Gods bountiful providence, in admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring bleſſings ſutable to her condition; and not from any ambitious emulation of others grandeur.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:106528:22"/>
            <p>Such as is ſaid was her more private converſe with God. What was more obvious to the eyes of men, was very exemplary; whether we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider her deportment in the publick Congregation, or in her Family duties.</p>
            <p>In the publick Prayers in the Church (as alſo in the Family) her Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, outward geſture, and voice was ever moſt decent, humble, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verent with all evidences of a broken, contrite, ſerious, and ſervent ſpirit; expreſſing greateſt affection, with ſuch diligent and undiſtracted attention, without the leaſt ſhew of Oſtentation, that whoſoever obſerved her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment, could not but conclude,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 1.12, 13. Sancti ſine vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mant ad Deum. — Inſpirante Spiritu ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto apud De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um per ſilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium Sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum clamor auditur. <hi>Aug. Ser.</hi> 90. <hi>de temp.</hi>
               </note> that her Prayers (like <hi>Hannah</hi>'s) were more the work of the heart, than of the lips; or as it is ſaid of <hi>Moſes,</hi> that he cried to the Lord, even whilſt he kept ſilence, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.15.</p>
            <p>And that ſhe might not loſe the opportunity of enjoying any part of Divine Service, ſhe ever came to the Church before the beginning of Prayers, at the uſual hour.</p>
            <p>Nor had ſhe leſs regard to the Preaching of the Word. She would not miſs one Sermon, whilſt ſhe was able to go abroad. And ſhe conſtantly writ every Sermon, which every morning ſhe peruſed in the following Week: that ſhe might both better digeſt in Meditation, what ſhe had heard; and that her memory might better guide her in the contexture with the next Diſcourſe upon the ſame Subject.</p>
            <p>This Ordinance ſhe ever highly prized, eſteeming it one of the greateſt bleſſings it pleaſed the divine bounty to vouchſafe her.<note place="margin">Iſa. 66.2. Heb. 5.14. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1 Joh. 1.1. 1 Theſ. 5.21.</note> She was one of them, that trembles at his Word, which ever had an awe upon her ſpirit. Having her ſenſes exerciſed by reaſon of uſe (or habit obtained by cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary diligence) to diſcern between good and evil, ſo that ſhe was able to try the ſpirits, whether they were of God, and to prove all things, that ſhe might hold faſt that which is good; when ſhe was ſatisfied concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſoundneſs of the Doctrine, and Orthodoxy of the Preacher, ſhe would receive that which was ſo Preached, not as the word of man, but as it is indeed the Word of God,<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 2.13. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Acts 16, 14.</note> which had therefore an effectual opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on her believing heart: which (like <hi>Lydia</hi>'s) was ever open to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with all reverence to the things which were ſpoken. She conſidered that ſhe was at that place and time, eſpecially preſent before God, to hear what his Embaſſadour had in commiſſion to ſay to her; what ſhe was about; and to what end ſhe came thither, <hi>viz.</hi> to learn, not to carp at or deſpiſe what ſhe heard. She was ſo judicious, as to diſcern the Preachers weakneſs (if he were ſuch) but yet had ſo much reverence to the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, and charity to the Miniſter, as to pity, not deſpiſe his weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Her humble heart, like the low Valley,<note place="margin">Corfluit enim aqua ad hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militatem convallis; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natat de tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moribus collis. <hi>Aug. Ser.</hi> 27. <hi>de verb. Domini.</hi>
               </note> entertained thoſe refreſhing Streams, which were ſent forth from the Fountain of Life; that could find no place of abode in a proud and cenſorious heart.</p>
            <p>Such was her pious regard to the Preaching of the Word. Nor had ſhe leſs reſpect to both thoſe holy Sacraments, which our Saviour ordained in his Church, in their reſpective uſe. Therefore when any Infant was to be Baptized, ſhe would ever attend with all reverence to the whole Office;
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:106528:23"/>rejoycing to behold a new Member admitted with ſuch ſolemnity into the Church; fervently and affectionately joyning with the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Prayers to God for it.</p>
            <p>As for the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, ſhe ſo greatly hungred after that ſpiritual food, that ſhe would not loſe the opportunity of one Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when (as at the feaſt of Eaſter) it was more frequently adminiſtred. What care ſhe took that ſhe might be a fit gueſt at that heavenly Feaſt, may appear by that paſſage, which was before obſerved out of her Papers: hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling her ſelf in a private ſolemn Faſt, the week before the Sacrament, that ſhe might by ſelf-examination become more ſenſible of her failings and wants; whereby ſhe might be prepared with more eager appetite, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to partake of thoſe comforts, which are there repreſented, ratified, and exhibited to every true Believer. And it appears by her own careful ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, that the fruit was anſwerable; in theſe words, <hi>Wherein</hi> (ſaith ſhe) <hi>I received much comfort.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have never obſerved in any Communicant greater evidence of humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, reverence, and devotion than in her reception of the holy Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; which together with her eager deſire, careful preparation, and diligent attendance upon that divine Ordinance, was a ſure argument of that great comfort which ſhe received in the uſe of it.</p>
            <p>The laſt Sacrament which ſhe ever received, was upon <hi>June</hi> 9. 1672. being the occaſion of her coming abroad, after a long weakneſs, which had confined her to her houſe, and was indeed the laſt time of her being abroad. She had a longing deſire to receive it in the publick Congregation (hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once before received it in private, by reaſon of her great weakneſs) which was (as God was pleaſed to order it) to the great prejudice of her health. That morning, more than her ſtrength could bear, ſhe roſe two hours earlier than of a long time before ſhe had done: the day was very rugged, and the air unmild; ſo that in all probability her coming abroad was a great cauſe of increaſing her diſtemper. But with deſire ſhe deſired to eat with us this Paſſover before her approaching Death.<note place="margin">Luke 22.15.</note> Being therefore conducted by her tender Husband to the Church, after Sermon ſhe received the Sacrament with more than ordinary Devotion: which was indeed to her a bleſſed <hi>viaticum</hi> before her departure hence,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> into her heavenly Manſion (which was but the tenth day after) where ſhe now enjoys him immediately (without the uſe of Ordinances) whom her Soul loved.</p>
            <p>Beſides this conſcientious attendance on, and careful improvement of the Ordinances, and publick means of Salvation; her earneſt deſire of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and increaſe of Grace was evident by the great pleaſure ſhe took in godly diſcourſe and conference; wherein that part which ſhe uſually bore was propoſal of ſuch Queries, in which ſhe deſired further ſatisfaction; with ſome affectionate expreſſions arguing ſelf-application, and that ſeldom (if ever) without contrite tears. Her humble and broken ſpirit, would ever judge her ſelf unworthy of offered comfort; yet would earneſtly liſten to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:106528:23"/>it, deſiring with <hi>David,</hi> to hear the voice of joy and gladneſs, admiring it,<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.8.</note> and not willfully rejecting what ſhe was urged to receive; entertaining each argument with joyful tears, which might give her any aſſurance, or hope of divine favour through Chriſt, on whoſe alone merits ſhe wholly relied, trampling under-foot all conceit of any worth of her own Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>And when there was any occaſion to ſpeak to her by way of advice, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, or admonition; with what complacency would ſhe receive it? What ever was ſaid on ſuch occaſion to her (with any evidence from the Word, that it was the Will of God and a declared duty) was ever readily admitted without the leaſt reluctancy or heſitancy. For the true fear of God, and his love ſhed abroad in her heart conſtrained her obedience. Yea, ſo careful was ſhe, that ſhe might not in any thing offend; that ſhe would make requeſt (where ſhe was confident of Faithfulneſs) to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved; of which I had this experiment. Upon our firſt acquaintance, when I was but newly ſettled in the Rectory, having a fit opportunity, none being preſent, ſhe thus beſpoke me: <hi>Sir,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Herein ſhe imitated that gracious Queen <hi>Anna Bullen,</hi> who was her great Grandfathers Aunt. <hi>Vid.</hi> Book of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, <hi>Vol.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 371.</note> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>God hath ſent you hither to take care of our Souls; therefore I intreat you, that you would not ſpare, faithfully to reprove whatever you ſhall ſee amiſs in me.</hi> For ſhe eſteemed faithful reproof to be a requiſite and neceſſary duty both of a Miniſter, and of a Friend. Accordingly having ſuch encouragement, I reſolved upon that ground, to deal freely with her, as I ſhould have occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. But I ever obſerved ſuch an uniform regard of duty, and care of her deportment at all times, and towards all perſons; that during the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue of her Life, nothing offered it ſelf, which any ordinary diſcretion could think worthy of a reproof: ſo careful ſhe was to practiſe the Apoſtles preſcript, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.15. <hi>That ye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> may be blameleſs, and harmleſs,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Such was her Converſation towards God: Therefore,</p>
            <p n="2">2. She could not miſs to order her Converſation aright towards all ſorts of men: which indeed was moſt lovely and exemplary, her light ſhining forth, to the glory of her heavenly Father, and the great refreſhment of ſuch pious Souls as had the happineſs to know her. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. She was of a lovely and amiable comportment towards all with whom ſhe did converſe; being altogether unaccuſtomed to any moroſity, or diſdain, even towards inferiours, though of loweſt rank. In her enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments ſhe was alwaies chearful (which was indeed her conſtant temper) and even her mirths were not only innocent, but alſo grateful.</p>
            <p>And as her good nature inclined her to love all mankind; Grace di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected her more eſpecially to affect thoſe that were (in her judgement) beloved of God. She had learned <hi>David</hi>'s leſſon,<note place="margin">Pſalm 15.</note> to honour them that fear the Lord; and alſo followed his example, in placing all her delight in the Saints that are in the Earth, whom ſhe eſteemed of all men the moſt excellent. Theſe were ever dear to her, though differing in judgement from her in ſuch things wherein we ought to bear with one another. For ſhe loved Religion, not Diviſion.<note place="margin">Religio, à ligando.</note> When ſhe admitted any into the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of her nearer Friends; as ſhe was exactly judicious to guide her
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:106528:24"/>choice (wherein ſhe was ſeldom, if ever, miſtaken) ſo ſhe was faithful, and conſtant, to continue her affection without change, or ſuſpicion of change;<note place="margin">Joh. 13.1.</note> imitating therein her Saviour, in loving them unto the End.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Nor was ſhe only curteous, but alſo innocent, and harmleſs in all her deportment: being of a meek, quiet, peaceable ſpirit, ſhe became an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Miſtriſs of her Paſſions. I cannot remember, that I ever ſaw her diſcompoſed by any prevalent paſſion. Her conſtant frame was interwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with chearfulneſs, and ſeriouſneſs: uſually chearful and pleaſant in humane concerns, ſerious in Divine. But never (that upon enquiry I could hear of) either tranſported with anger, clouded with ſullenneſs, ſwallowed up with overmuch ſorrow, or exorbitant in her joys: though ſhe hath not wanted occaſions enough, no doubt (ſince none can be free) to excite and provoke paſſion. None could better know how to bear and digeſt an injury; nor could any be more fearful to do one. None more loth to take offence, and none more careful of giving any. Though ſhe could ſee as ſoon as another, any undecent, and provocative miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanor of an inferiour: yet ſhe knew how to connive, without any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice towards the offendor: for that Monſter had no place in her calm heart. If at any time ſhe found her ſelf miſtaken in faulting another (though a Servant) ſhe would be really ſorry for it: and I have heard her ſay, that in ſuch caſe, ſhe would not grudge to ask them forgiveneſs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Her Charity and Bounty in giving, was beyond her Eſtate, which yet was plentiful to her own content, and in which ſhe found no want, but to ſatisfie her eager deſire to communicate, and do more good. Though a leſs Eſtate, than ſhe had, would have pleaſed her thankful and humble heart; yet the greateſt would have been little enough to have ſupplied her Beneficience; being ſo devoted to practiſe that Apoſtolical injunction, <hi>viz.</hi> to be careful to maintain good Works for neceſſary uſes,<note place="margin">Tit. 3.4. Pſa. 92.13. &amp;c. 1.3.46.2. Ezek. 27. Rev. 22.</note> that ſhe might not be unfruitful. Having been planted in the Houſe of the Lord, by that River of the Sanctuary, whoſe Streams make glad the City of God, ſhe flouriſhed in his Courts, bringing forth her fruit in its due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, yea, even in old Age ſtill flouriſhing.</p>
            <p>Verily her Charity was moſt exemplary, whether we conſider its mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, manner, principle, or End.</p>
            <p>Her end in giving was not for Oſtentation or vain glory, that men might ſee and applaud her Charity. For ſo much as was poſſible, ſhe ſo concealed it from others knowledge, that none but ſuch inſtruments as ſhe muſt neceſſarily make uſe of to convey her Alms, and the parties re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved might be conſcious of it. Her only deſign was to glorifie God in doing good to his poor Creatures,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.40. In this alſo ſhe imitated (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to her ability) her noble Anceſtor Queen <hi>Anna Bullen,</hi> Book of Mart. <hi>ubi ſupra.</hi>
               </note> and to his living Temples, which our bleſſed Saviour takes as kindly as if done to himſelf.</p>
            <p>The meaſure of her Alms was liberal and bountiful. Her gifts were diſtributed with a full hand, as her ſtore could furniſh her with ſupplies. For from the time of her Marriage, her moſt kind and indulgent Husband allowed her (upon her requeſt for this purpoſe) a conſiderable monthly
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:106528:24"/>which was freely committed to her diſpoſe: of which ſhe was ſo ſparing from other uſes, that ſhe would rather abridge her ſelf in ſome things that her condition might require, than ſhe would pinch her Almes, which was ever proportionable to the caſe ſhe had under conſideration.</p>
            <p>The way and manner ſhe obſerved in her beneficence, was ever directed by Prudence. For ſeeing ſuch largeſs muſt neceſſarily diſable her from the frequency which ſhe deſired (that practice being indeed a great part of her joys) therefore ſhe would ever make prudent choice, not only of the way whereby, but alſo of the Party whom ſhe ſhould relieve.</p>
            <p>As for the Party to whom ſhe would extend her Bounty; that ſhe might not caſt away her Money, either through indiſcretion or vain glory, ſhe was ever careful to diſcharge this as a Duty, in obedience unto Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand: not heedleſly giving, but where ſhe was perſwaded that ſhe ought to do it: obſerving that advice, <hi>Withhold not good from them to whom it is due,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 3.27. <hi>Heb.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>à Dominis ejus, Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num illum ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficit neceſſitate &amp; te Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatorem Deus. <hi>Jun. in loc.</hi> Pſal. 119.72.</note> 
               <hi>when it is in the power of thine hand to do it.</hi> She would therefore give only there, where ſhe thought it was a due required by God; either by way of recompence for their pains, who laboured and watched for her ſoul, (<hi>Heb.</hi> 12.13.) as ſhe was directed by Gods Word, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.12, 13. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.11. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6. (For ſhe had learned with holy <hi>David,</hi> to prefer the Law of Gods mouth before worldly Riches) or by way of compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, where there was real, and not pretended neceſſity. She was perſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that God required her to help, when he was pleaſed to preſent her with ſuch an object of Charity. But then did ſhe judge, ſhe had got the fitteſt object, when this neceſſity was accompanied with ſincere Piety,<note place="margin">Omnibus nos debitores fecit communis hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitas; ſed fidelibus vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum arctius ſpiritualìs cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nationis, quam Dominus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter nos ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit. <hi>Calv.</hi> in Gal. 6.10.</note> according to the Apoſtles preſcript, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10. <hi>As we have opportunity let us do good to all men, eſpecially to them who are of the houſhold of Faith.</hi> There ſhe accounted her Charity moſt due.</p>
            <p>But ſhe was not only careful to make right choice of the Party whom ſhe ought to relieve, but alſo of that way and means, whereby ſhe might do them moſt good, and her Charity make for the greateſt advantage. The Hungry ſhe would Feed, and procure Cloaths for the Naked, and comfort the Sick with ſuch things as ſhe had. That of <hi>Job.</hi> 29.13. might fitly be applied to her: <hi>The bleſſing of thoſe that were ready to periſh, came upon her, and ſhe cauſed the Widdows heart to ſing for joy.</hi> She was the poor Orphans Mother, taking ſome of them into her own Family,<note place="margin">Ita ſingulis ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am pecuniam dividebat, ut ſingulis neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarium erat, <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eron. Ep.</hi> 27, Job 31.16.</note> others were kept to School, others were placed forth as Apprentices with her Money. For ſome poor Families ſhe would purchaſe Cows, that the Children might have Milk; or what other waies ſhe could deviſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to help poor and decayed people. Thus ſhe with-held not the poor from their deſire, nor would ſhe cauſe the eyes of the Widdow to fail. Nor was this her practice for a fit, or ſeldom, but conſtant, and continued till her dying day, ſhe was not weary of well-doing, nor did ſhe fail to the laſt; leaving order even at her End for further diſtribution of the remainder, yet undiſpoſed of. No doubt, but ſhe now enjoyeth a plentiful Crop of that bleſſed Seed; and her Works follow her.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:106528:25"/>
            <p>Such was her converſe with others, who were not her Family Relations. What her deportment was towards them, I ſhall ſpeak the leſs, becauſe I cannot ſay enough. She that thus walked with God, and whoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation towards all others, was ſuch as is before declared, muſt needs be moſt benigne and reſpective to all her Relations. To mention her goodneſs towards each of them particularly, would but too much grate upon their grieved ſpirits, and renew their yet freſh ſorrows for ſo great a loſs.</p>
            <p>This I may preſume to ſay, that no Husband could loſe a more loving, reſpective, obedient, and in each regard a better Wife, and Friend: No Child a more tender, loving, careful Mother: No Servant a more lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, meek, provident, indulgent Lady, that could more deſire and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour their good. And this not only in reference to their body and outward man; but with more eſpecial reſpect to their Souls, and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſtate. It was ever her great deſire and careful endeavour, that all who were near her, ſhould ſerve God with her, and that ſhe might ever find them in the fear of God. Nor could any thing more grieve her, than at any time to ſee any of them offend or ſin againſt God.</p>
            <p>As to her carriage in all things towards her Husband, and his recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally toward her. I have never obſerved in any married pair a greater mutual complacency, than betwixt them two. They lived together as if they had but one Heart, and one Will in all things: that which was pleaſing to either, was ever moſt eligible to the other. Yea, who ever obſerved any difference of opinion in them, or the leaſt diſcontent, or ever heard any conteſt between them; whoſe only ſtrife was, whether of them ſhould more pleaſe and gratifie the other?</p>
            <p>But inſtead of larger reports of her gracious and loving reſpects to her neareſt Relations, theſe few notes following may ſuffice to declare her affection to them, and care for them: which I have tranſcribed out of her own Papers, prepared five years ago (ſhe having long laboured un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an Hectick diſtemper) and which ſhe delivered with her own hands, one to her Husband, and the other to her only Son, the day before her Death.</p>
            <p>Some part of the Paper to her Husband being dated <hi>Feb.</hi> 20. 1667. is as followeth,</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My dear Heart Sir <hi>Thomas Wharton,</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R good and gracious God will be thy great ſupport and comfort in all conditions, and will make up all Relations, without whom none could have given any contentment. We have by his mercies lived more happy daies, than almoſt any: but changes muſt come to us, as well as to all others. Therefore let us be thankful for all our good we have enjoyed; and be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and ready to give up what is deareſt to us, when he calls, who will do nothing to hurt us, being our moſt loving Father in Chriſt, who has bought us with his precious blood. This I believe, Lord help my unbelief, and give me
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:106528:25"/>to live the life of Faith and Thankſgiving, and prepare me for his Will, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Life or Death. I am very infirm, but heart whole, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Then making mention of her only Son,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Of whom <hi>(ſaith ſhe)</hi> I need not deſire your taking care, for he is yours as much as mine, and I know you love him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I would fain have him much in your company, or under your eye. Though I know, his Youth and your Gravity will not altogether ſute; yet I hope you will allow him grains, and he yield you all obedience of Love, as well as Fear. I ſhall need to ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of his Marriage: for I think we both agree, in deſiring he may meet in the firſt place with Piety, Vertue, and a good Extraction. And if any Wealth or Beauty attend upon theſe, let it come: they are not ill Servants, though unfit to be uppermoſt in our deſires or eſteem. If God give his bleſſing, a little will be enough; if not, enough will be too little to ſatisfie the covet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous deſire: from which good God deliver him. I had rather his Education might inſtruct him to uſe that little be will have, well; than to covet more, to ſpend ill.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Paper to her Son followeth <hi>verbatim.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My dear <hi>Philip,</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Pray God bleſs you; and he who has raiſed you from many illneſſes and weakneſſes, raiſe your heart and life to ſome degree anſwerable to theſe great mercies, and all other which I am not able to reckon up. I am at this time, I praiſe God, well, and have no illneſs on me; but grow Old, and infirm often: which makes me deſire to leave ſomething in charge with you, which you may read, and remember your old Mother by.</p>
                  <p>In the firſt place, Love and fear God; and preſs and ſtrive every day to increaſe more and more in the love and ſervice of him, in whom you live, move, and have your being. There is no Wiſdom or Policy like it. And the more you converſe with Gods Word, and his People, the more you will find it, and the better you will like it: For in his Service is perfect freedom. Let me conjure you to let no day go without reading the holy Scripture, and other good Books, as you have leiſure; you will find them excellent company. And do not only Read, but conſider what you Read, to remember it. I ſhould be very glad, you would early fit, and prepare for the communion of the bleſſed Body and Blood of Chriſt; not raſhly becauſe others do it, but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſedly; finding the want of it, and the preciouſneſs of it; which may give you a true hunger and thirſt after it, and all other Ordinances of God; upon which, I pray, attend very diligently. Next, Honour and Love your King, and look upon Rebellion as the ſin of Witchcraft. Obſerve and obey all his juſt commands; and what ever they be, pray for him, and ſubmit, and ſuffer what you cannot obey of them; but never riſe, nor murmur at any lawful Authority, though it be never ſo croſs to your own humour; but pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently bear what you cannot amend. Laſtly, Reverence, Honour, Obey, and Love your Father. Obey his commands, obſerve his inſtructions, mark his
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:106528:26"/>reproofs to prevent the need of them any more. And let them not make you love his company leſs; for it is his kindneſs. When he is angry, be your very mild, and diſcreet in your replies; and do not expoſtulate with him, but own your fault, which will quickly obtain pardon: for he loves you dearly, and ſo would I fain have you do him. Be careful of him in Age or Sickneſs: Love to be in his company. And alwaies chooſe the beſt company; for there is no good got in ill, mean company. And avoid, as much as you can, all Debauchery, and theſe that are ſo. Let the fear of God firſt prevail with you; then the pleaſing of your Father, and your dead Mothers injunctions, when ſhe was alive. And conſider well your Vow made in Baptiſm, which though it were then promiſed by others, yet you are bound to perform now, as your Catechiſe teacheth you. To which end conſider the Church-Catechiſe well, and there you will find your obligation: which I beſeech God to enable you to ſtrive to perform in reſiſting the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil; and Loving our good God, and our Neighbours. I would give you warning of two ſorts of People; the Flatterer, and the Backbiter; and of being either your ſelf. And when any flatters you to your Face, be not pleaſed with it, but have a more ſtrict guard upon your behaviour and actions, and examine whether it belong to you or no; if it do, give God the glory; if not, take that occaſion to endeavour after being what you would be thought to be. And if you hear any ſpeak ill of others, who do not deſerve it: Look to your ſelf; for you are like to have the ſame, when your back is turn'd. My dear Child, be careful of your waies; and let not theſe things I ſay, be ſlighted by you: for they come from one that loves you, and wiſheth your welfare, I aſſure you; by Name your old Mother,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Mary Wharton.</signed>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Feb. 26. 1667.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>By this it may appear, what pious and loving regard ſhe had to her deareſt, and neareſt Relations; that after her Death they might have this (as her laſt Legacy) to put them in mind of her dear affection to them, and of her moſt godly deſire of their ſpiritual welfare after her depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. She had reſerved theſe Papers, by her in her Cabinet, till ſhe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended her approaching Diſſolution. And then though exceedingly faint, yet with a chearful countenance (which had ever been her ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry aſpect,<note place="margin">Index animi vultus.</note> an argument of a ſerene mind) ſhe with her own hands tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted them to theirs.</p>
            <p>And ſince we are in hand with Paper-evidences of her pious Vertues, it ſhall not be amiſs in this place, to inſert the Teſtimony of the Right Reverend Biſhop of <hi>Elphin,</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> (formerly mentioned) who had ſpent much of the time with them, during the troubles in <hi>Ireland,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he had the opportunity of intimate acquaintance with the Family; and therefore moſt able to give a good account of their Converſation. Having received intelligence of her Death, he writes this conſolatory Epiſtle to her ſoffowful Husband, from <hi>Elphin.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:106528:26"/>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>ALthough the deceaſe of your pious Conſort, and ſenſe of your loſs muſt needs work an exceeding great grief: Yet the conſideration of her holy Life, religious End, and the hope of receiving her again, cannot but revive and comfort you. I need not tell you, that her publick carriage was an exact Commentary upon that deſcription, which <hi>Solomon</hi>'s M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ther gives of a Vertuous Woman. Her gentle, diſcreet, well-temper'd demeanour, all that ever knew her, or had the happineſs to converſe with her, will without bluſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be witneſſed by them. But that which ſets her beyond all verbal praiſes: As ſhe was of a Vertuous, ſo of a Gracious diſpoſition. I ſpeak it unfainedly: The fear of God was planted in her heart: ſhe had not an outward ſemblance, or ſhew of Piety, but the Power of Godlineſs; which ſhe manifeſted in her conſcionable frequenting of the publick Miniſtry; with <hi>Mary</hi> treaſuring up the Word in her heart, and bringing it forth into action. What hours were ſpent in her Cloſet, in Prayer, Reading, Meditation, which was a great means of her ſpiritual progreſs in Knowledge and Grace, and the ſureſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and ſeal of ſincerity, is beſt known to your ſelf. It pleaſed God by a long and lingring Sickneſs, to mean her from the delights of this World, to carry her thoughts and deſires Heaven-ward, living fruitfully, and dying comfortably. The Lord ſhewed in her, that it is not in vain to ſerve him; and that a conſtant courſe of a Religious Life, will miniſter abundance of ſweet conſolation at the hour of Death, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>And in another Letter of a much later Date, having occaſion to make mention of her, he hath theſe words, <hi>Little is nothing, and much not enough to be recorded of her Piety, Loyalty, Charity, and Devotion. Her own Works will praiſe her in the gates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much I thought good to Tranſcribe from the Letters of that Holy and Reverend Prelate, as an unqueſtionable confirmation of what I have declared in this <hi>Narrative.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto we have had a general account of ſome remarks in her exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary Life: And even as ſhe lived ſo ſhe died.<note place="margin">Qualis vita, Finis ita.</note> Indeed a great part of her Life was but as it were a lingring Death. For many years before her Death, ſhe was afflicted with an Aſthmatical diſtemper, which cauſed (as I conceive) an Hectick, under which ſhe laboured till ſhe left this troubleſome World. No means was left unaſſayed by her loving and careful Husband; but Nature was by degrees ſo far ſpent and weakened, that the continual uſe of Cordials preſcribed by the moſt expert Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans could not repair, much leſs reſtore it, but only a little prolong, and draw out the infirm thread of her daily-dying-life. She that had ſpent the daies of her Youth, and her more healthful years ſo ſtudiouſly in the Service of God, muſt needs make the greateſt improvement of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation to the advantage of her inward man, which was daily renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as her outward man daily decayed; whilſt ſhe lived in a continual expectation of her Diſſolution.</p>
            <p>This gradual decay of natural vigour, together with her waſted ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:106528:27"/>and extream ſhortneſs of breath conſidered; we could not expect, that when ever it ſhould pleaſe God to viſit her with any extraordinary Diſtemper, threatning Death, ſhe ſhould ſpeak much, though ſhe much deſired to do it. Hence it came to paſs, that we want the verbal evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of her dying conſolations, as alſo the benefit of her laſt advice, and dying admonitions to us, who are left behind to bewail our loſs of ſo great a treaſure. She ſeemed to fore-ſee thus much diverſe years before her Death, having had ſo frequent experience of her inability, to ſpeak after any more than uſual motion of her Body, when the humours were ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. This might be one cauſe (beſides thoſe other which we ſpoke of) that ſhe prepared thoſe Papers to her Husband and Son, to ſupply the want of words, in caſe of ſuch feared inab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lity. Accordingly (as was moſt probable) it came to paſs: For that very day, after ſhe had received the Sacrament, ſhe retired to her Chamber, which ſhe never afterward left, till her earthly part was carried forth to burial. From which time her ſpeech ſo failed her by degrees, that at laſt ſhe did rather whiſper than ſpeak (and very difficulty even that) which likewiſe failed ſome ſhort while before her Death.</p>
            <p>With what remarkable Patience and chearfulneſs did ſhe entertain theſe laſt aſſaults of her accuſtomed Diſtempers, ſmiling even in the face of Death, as being confident of the Conqueſt, though ſhe muſt die in the Conflict? What ever pain, or faintings ſhe endured; you ſhould hear no complaint, or obſerve any evidence of diſcontent, but of chearful and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſubmiſſion to the Will of her heavenly Father. So long as ſhe was any waies able ſhe ceaſed not to evidence her earneſt deſire of, and great delight and complacency ſhe took in our Prayers, and in each conſolatory diſcourſe then directed to her. Her careful, and then ſorrowful Husband being in Prayer with her, not long before her departure, though ſtrength and voice ſeemed utterly to have failed, yet ſhe ſtrained her ſelf to utter an audible, and affectionate <hi>Amen,</hi> at the end of his Prayer, wherein he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned her up to the Lord. Immediatly before her Death I was intreated by her mournful Husband to perform that Office, when ſhe now ſeemed inſenſible of any thing ſaid or done: Yet thoſe that kneeled by her, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by the motion of her Hand (her Face being turned from the Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide) that ſhe was not without ſome apprehenſion of thoſe things which were uttered in Prayer, in her behalf; and conceived that ſhe would have endeavoured to have ſaid <hi>Amen</hi> in the Concluſion, but could not utter it.</p>
            <p>Thus as ſhe lived in Prayer, with it ſhe took leave of the World, to go to her Saviour; where ſhe is partaker of his Prayer, which he put up for her, and all his Elect, whilſt he lived on Earth, <hi>viz.</hi> that they may be with him, where he is; that they may behold his Glory, which the Father hath given him: Which that We alſo may with Her behold; let us fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low her Example, and we ſhall not fail of her Happineſs.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
